個人開會㗎啦嚇，噉樣誒，大家如果望完咧，請坐翻埋去嚇。
即係。
我我當救人啦。
都夠人嘅，阿阿行姐行開咗都夠。
四個啊嘛。
一二三四。
嗰陣時，我哋揾緊限制入嚟。誒，有副主席啊嚟咗㗎。
叫埋佢入嚟咯。如果只蛋過咗。
係，冇錯。
我晏晝先做，中午再過嚟。
得啦，夠人啦。
好啊！誒，各位同事，我哋夠人開會啦嚇。咁咧就。
誒，首先我哋可以請誒政府同埋西九嘅代表入嚟誒。
會議室先。
誒，早晨。
噉啊！因應大家嘅要求咧，就今日咧西九管理局咧就帶同咧個西九文化公園嘅模型咧，就畀大家喺度睇睇。
咁咧，誒，咁咧就。
頭先好多同事都望過啦，咁咧首先咧誒。
如果等佢哋，
坐好之後咧，噉我哋先邀請咧，就民政事務局常任秘書長阿馮太咧，同埋誒西九嘅代表咧，就介紹下我哋誒。
C.B.固二一零六六啊，縮十四開份十五零一固零一嘅文件。
噉啊！請啊，馮太。好啊！誒，早晨，各位多謝主席。誒，西九管理局咧喺舊年七月咧係向各位委員咧係介紹。
初步設計同埋管理上面嘅構思嘅咁今日咧就會向各位匯報兩項關於西九公園嘅發展，一個咧就係最新嘅設計工作。咁頭先主席都提到啦，喺呢度中間有一個嘅模型啦。咁一陣間誒管理局方面咧會用投影片咧再作詳細嘅介紹嘅。咁另外一個咧就係會向各位咧匯報關於西九。
嘅公誒第個公共空間個扶例，咁一陣間亦都會誒西九管理局各方面會詳細去介紹。我呢度想只係想講一講咧，就係西九公園同埋黑黑劇場嘅建造工程咧，預計係會今年嘅第三季咧係展開嘅。但係咧，我哋明白到咧，公眾人士咧都希望能夠繼續係可以享用到西九嘅公共空間啦。
所以管理局咧，將會係喺今年下半年咧，就會喺西九咧用地嘅西端咧，係開放一個臨時公園。咁咧，我哋亦都叫呢個做係苗圃公園嘅，因為裏邊係有啲嘅樹苗喺嗰度咧，係去擺放，將來係會種喺西九嘅公園裏邊嘅。咁亦都咧更加重要嘅咧，除咗係有呢個臨時嘅公園之外咧，仲要咧仲會咧係係策劃一係列。
嘅節目同埋活動咧，喺呢個苗圃公園裏邊進行，等市民咧可以享用呢一片嘅用地嘅。
噉我頭先亦都提到咧，係有呢一個嘅誒西九文化區公眾休憩用地嘅附例嘅一個嘅草案版本啦。誒整體嚟講咧，西九管理局咧，希望能夠咧用最少嘅限制咧嚟到係管理將來佢哋嘅公共空間嘅。咁因為呢一套附例咧係需要經過立法會咧係通過，係一份有約束力嘅文。
文件啦，所以咧係唔適宜咧，就每一個範疇咧都寫得太個具細無遺。咁但係咧，西九管理局咧係會有一係列嘅指引咧嚟到協助佢哋係去管理呢一個西九公共空間嘅場地咁方面。特別係咧，如果係需要有一啲嘅改動嘅時候咧，亦都係比較方便噉樣去作出回應管。
管理場地嘅需要嘅，咁頭一陣間咧，管理局亦都去介紹佢哋呢一套嘅指引啦，包括係街頭表演啦、户外節目啦、同埋拍攝同攝影嘅範疇嘅指引嘅。噉我哋打算咧喺完成呢一個嘅諮詢各個持份者，包括區議會啦、文化藝術工作者、街頭表演嘅誒工作者之外。
後咧，我哋希望喺今年第二季或者第三季，最遲係第三季咧，會將呢個疑議嘅附例咧嚟提交立法會係審議嘅。我而家先請咧管理局嘅行政總裁連立志先生咧，同大家講幾句。稍後咧，柏志高先生會向各位係作一個介紹。好啊，Mr.連。
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I guess I just wanted to make a couple of opening comments in light of the agenda today. Members would be aware that I have tendered my resignation and will be leaving the authority at the end of July this year. I just wanted to.
重複到這個委員會，與我們有過相當的互動，這段期間，我在此期間，這是一個無可否認的榮幸，我從2011年7月加入西蘭羣島項目以來，我深信這個願景。
And that the West Kowloon Cultural District will be a significant arts and cultural landmark in Hong Kong, and that everyone in Hong Kong can be proud of it, and that it will be an important legacy for the future of this city. I'll be leaving with a sense of satisfaction and some pride in what.
所被達成由我的同事和大量參與這個項目的人士在過去四年的任內。
Most importantly, we've built a very competent and dedicated team who will continue to take the project forward with my successor, and that search is underway at the moment.
As members will note from the reports today, and the ongoing interest in issues in relation to the park, we have made significant progress. Clearly, the model is an important indicator of that. The opening of the temporary park in the middle of this year will be an important first step in.
maintaining public access to the site while we're going through the building, we're also planning to develop the area surrounding Artis Square into a mini West Kaluun cultural district, and one of the things we'll talk about today is the reconfiguration of some of our performing arts venues to reflect both.
時間壓力、issues related to the railway project。
and so that we can indicate some real progress on the overall direction of the project, so as to what will be completed by 2020.
I think all of these underline our commitment of early delivery of the park, as well as some of the arts and cultural facilities, and I think that's an important issue in light of the discussions that have taken place here. The park is a really important addition to the public space of Hong Kong. We see.
作為我們之前所指示的，保持開放的構想，反映香港人民的願望和抱負。我現在要請我的同事鄧肯·佩斯科特，我們的首席運營官，帶領我們瞭解在發展方面所做的工作。
So far, the proposed open space bylaws and the guidelines that sit underneath it. And I look forward over the coming months to a couple more sessions with you before we say goodbye later in July. Thanks, Mr. Chairman.
OK。
誒，法例。
主席，這係 Quite Quite 一個詳細嘅 Presentation，所以我會過 Through 它比較快啲，Starting First 係 The Update on The Park Development。
just to give members an orientation, the park itself.
comprises the space at the bottom of the slide.
down here.
And has a number of major features: the large green area.
The free space black box here.
The art pavilion here.
和 existing structures which include the.
ventilation shafts for the west, western harbour crossing and the airport express railway.
The other section that I want to draw members' attention to is this north, in the northern part, which is the temporary park, which we, as we've indicated, will be opening in the middle of this year. So, there are a number of features within the park that are already
identifiable， and the work will start on this. We hope on the ground again towards the middle of this year.
There are inevitably with a site like this a number of site constraints.
Not least, of course, the fact that we have the Western Harbour Crossing going right through the middle of the site, and we have part of the Airport Express railway line going through another section of the of the site.
this of course constrains the development that can take place within the site as a whole. Nevertheless, we've looked very carefully at linking.
the park into the rest of the West Island Cultural District development, as well as into adjacent areas such as elements.
And the pedestrian throughput will allow for very free access for for visits visitors.
Of course, one of the most impressive and imposing elements will be the waterfront promenade.
It's worth saying that this will be inevitably developed in sections, comprising the section from here round to here, being the first section of the park, the rest being completed as and when the site comes available, obviously.
特別係作為作為結果，啲高速 rail發展。
There will be a number of features within the park which are intended to give an element of texture and dimension to the park, so that people will be able to use the park in a variety of different ways. This edge, double edge design will allow for both
height differential within the park and views out towards the harbour, but also within it will be embedded some of the retail and dining space that will be provided in the park, effectively hiding it and maximising the green space within the park area.
Of course, there will be a need for ancillary facilities, notably toilets, restaurants and other things. We've looked at this from the point of view of distances. We don't want people to have to.
travel large distances to find facilities, so they've been located within reasonable walking space from any of the locations within the park.
As I touched on before, there'll be a number of
Retail and dining opportunities. This is essentially the park, located as it is at the western end of the district. These will be located within.
The double edge here, and in due course in phase two towards the back end of the large green space.
會也會有啲支持，餐廳用餐設施，為黑盒有效地作為一個補充設施，到那黑盒劇場。
我 just like to finish off with some of the visuals to give members a better feeling for how the park will look when it's finished. As you can see here, the area
會有。
Both flat areas as well as raised areas, all of which will be disabled access. That's very important. We want no area to be blocked to anybody accessing the park.
looking down the waterfront promenade, you'll see the views will be spectacular right across here. But also, there will be areas of calm with extensive foliage and planting to ensure that people can enjoy the view without necessarily feeling that the whole of the park is watching them.
Nevertheless, there will be large open spaces. At the back of this site, you see the the large green area which will be available for use casually during non-event days and also for more formal events. With the support structure of the black box theatre, the free space providing.
機會是 for outdoor theatres and projections.
As I said, embedding the retail dining entertainment within the double edge will allow us to maximise the green area, but also provide essential facilities for visitors to the park.
Let me just very briefly now turn to the nursery park. As I said, this is at the northern section of the.
of the site.
It will be basically making use of what is an existing area, which has trees that will be transplanted into the park in due course. They're being essentially stored and tested out here.
但係， in addition， 有會 be event spaces。
四個event spaces， 一係呢個係一個現有的圓形區域，一個新區域要建，現有的綠地在中間的幼稚園公園，另一個區域在北邊。呢個會令到我們可以舉辦活動，亦都可以鼓勵市民喺整個發展期間都使用公園。
係。
One other issue that we intend to look at is how we can make this accessible from the adjacent areas. Of course, with the Western Harbour Crossing, there's very good bus connections here. The MTR connection through the Tsung Chung line, and we've been looking at how we ensure.
這 Access is maintained.
Throughout the period of this use of the temporary park.
One other idea we're exploring is the use of movable furniture within the park, so that people can set up space for themselves as well as take time to observe the events that we put in. And this is something we're looking at at the moment.
我哋想轉到開放空間的條例，因為當然呢個係一個我哋覺得有好多回饋嘅領域。市民都覺得我們應該公佈我們如何運作公園嘅方法論，而方法就係根據《西卡倫文化區管理局條例》，授權我們制定條例。
我。
As has already been mentioned, these will be subject to.
positive vetting by the legislative council and we will be submitting these bylaws for consideration in due course.
Let me stress one thing here. They will apply to all open space, not just the park spaces, but all open spaces within the West Kowloon Cultural District.
And just to give you a feeling for that, as you can see on this slide, the park space is substantial. But in addition, there are many areas, both along the promenade and within the cultural district itself, which will count towards public open space. Indeed, for example, on the top of the podium area for.
M plus， there will be a substantial open park space. All of these will be subject to the bylaws and guidelines in due course.
The philosophy, I think, is very important in this. We want the public spaces to be as free and open as possible.
While at the same time, of course, it must be safe for all users, and there must be the opportunity to ensure that compatible users can proceed at the same time. This needs this requires the West Kaluan Cultural District Authority to have minimum powers so that we can manage the park and open spaces.
properly on on behalf of the public.
在 preparing the bylaws, we have looked at the bylaws and regulations which apply in Hong Kong, obviously to the Leisure and Cultural Services Department Parks and Open Spaces, but also overseas, looking for the best practice models that we can look at for parks, pleasure grounds and places of.
amusement.
在 preparing the bylaws themselves, we've obviously had reference to the vision for the park—a quality green open space that would make Hong Kong proud, as well as its mission: a waterfront park to inspire, promote and encourage cultural pursuits for all. And I think that emphasis on encouragement of cultural pursuits is central to our.
approach.
We've taken into account views expressed by the public during a three-stage public engagement exercise, which took place between 2009 and 2011.
作為，以及最近的公眾調查，關於公園管理，，其中涉及問卷，以及小組討論，以及在去年5月至6月之間進行的討論。所以，我們真的正在努力聆聽公眾，並考慮他們的觀點。
所以，讓我非常簡潔地過一下過去的規則和指引。
as I said before, these will give us the relevant powers, but they must be supplemented so that people can understand not just the legal framework but also the practical implementation of how we will take forward the operation of the park and open space. So we will have guidelines to provide these operating details.
In addition to that, we expect all of the signage to be positive and encouraging.
and these are just a couple of examples where we want to say look, we may have to restrict access, but we won't say don't step on the ground. We'll say look.
Be careful not to step on this area. Allow our seedlings to grow, but feel free to hop, skip and jump on the paths. That's the appropriate place. So the the approach is more positive, because I I think that sets the scene for the whole attitude.
And of course, what we don't want to do is to say, don't do this, don't do that, don't enjoy yourselves. We actually want to say, enjoy yourselves in this open space and the park.
Of course, areas may have to be closed off for various reasons, for maintenance management, as well as for events and for public safety. So the guidelines intend to make it clear that this is something that will happen, but we want to strike a proper balance between special events and the daily use of
的公園和公共區域，由所有我們的顧客。
Let me stress: for the event guidelines, we will be giving priority to arts and cultural events as well as public events, because we feel that reflects the basic ethos of this park and open space areas.
Another area that was raised in a lot of the feedback that we've had concerns street performances.
嗯。
The basic bylaw will say that street performances will be encouraged, but of course will have to take place with permission. The intention is to encourage cooperation and mutual respect between street performers, businesses and other users.
We will require a permit, but.
access to those permits will be very simple and very straightforward, and is intended mainly to ensure that street performers can perform what they claim, but also that they can do so safely in an environment which is of course.
open to the public.
Beyond this very basic access requirement, we will be encouraging, as part of our overall approach to developing arts and culture, the West Caledonian Street Performer Programme, where more professional performers will be encouraged to develop their their
和會被給支持做。
另一個 area， which again.
has become an issue already within the the area that that is available is filming and photography. Now let me stress.
this is.
filming and photography for commercial and professional reasons, and we will require permission again for safety reasons. As well as, it is already very evident that a big film crew will bring a lot of people, a lot of equipment, and will occupy space within the park or the open space. This needs to be properly controlled. It is.
是 not intended in any way, shape or form to control.
individuals wishing to take
photographs themselves, their family, their friends or the environment. We would of course be encouraging that.
和的guidelines會make this very clear.
The bylaws will of course deal with public conduct, and these are drawn as much from the existing regulations in Hong Kong for other public spaces. But they're designed to apply minimum regulation on public conduct, mainly for safety considerations. We will of course be allowing ball games, bicycle riding and other.
啊！
casual uses of the park in areas where they are permitted and unless otherwise notified. Again, this is a safety issue. An issue that's come up many times is whether kite flying will be allowed. Yes, but with certain restrictions which are imposed upon us by, for example, civil aviation department because.
由於我們靠近於直升機起降場地，在該區域。
We will of course look to protect the environment within the park and deal with issues relating to litter, damage to facilities and of course protecting the trees, shrubs and other flora and fauna within the park.
Let me stress, selling of goods or services, begging and all the other forms of control that exist in other parks in Hong Kong will apply in the West Kowloon Cultural District area as well.
domestic pets will be permitted as long as they are under proper control, and the responsibility will be placed firmly on the owner or the
responsible person bringing those pets into the.
area.
no cars or vehicles unless authorised. It is supposed to be a park, and of course members will be well aware of the concept that all vehicular access to the Westcalleen Cultural District should be through the basement area. Of course.
We will have to provide access for disabled, for example, and public transport in appropriate locations. That will be covered within our management systems.
Contraventions, of course, these are part of the law. They will be provided for, attracting fines ranging from level one to level three. I'm sure members are very familiar with this.
powers will be required for our staff and other designated people to be able to require proof of identity.
May require a person to leave or attend the authority's office or indeed police station, and under the worst case scenario, of course, detain an offender until the police arrive if necessary. I would stress here that, of course, the key issue to all of these guidelines and the enforcement of the bylaws is the quality of the staff and staff training.
for all of our staff operating within the park and open space, will be a very key issue to make sure they understand both the philosophy and the practical requirements of the management of this sort of facility.
We are currently engaged in another round of stakeholder engagement. We have been to the Yaoqimeng District Council. We've consulted our own consultation panel with representatives from different sectors, and we had a session with open to all members from the 18 District Councils.
In parallel, we are engaging arts, culture and other groups that have an interest in the park and open space, as well of course as local street performers and the representatives of nearby residents. And of course, we're very, very pleased to have members' comments here today, which will also be taken into account as we final.
realise.
The by-laws preparation and the guidelines development.
We will of course continue to listen to views from different stakeholders, even once the bylaws and guidelines are in place.
And we will be refining the draft bylaws before we introduce them to Legco for positive vetting.
I think I'll stop there, Mr. Chairman. Thank you very much. Obviously, very happy to answer any questions.
Okay.
誒，再冇其他人補充。
如果冇咧，噉我哋進入我哋討論好嘛？每人四分鐘，聯問聯答啊，噉樣。首先咧就陳婉霞、毛曼、鄭，跟住就何秀蘭、陳志全，好嘛？陳婉霞。
多謝主席。
誒，阿連山臨離香港，祝你誒生活愉快，身體健康。
嗯。
點都好啦！喺過去我哋好多爭拗，呢個亦都香港嘅可愛。你有你嘅意見，我有我嘅意見，好嘛？不過希望你繼續對香港保留好印象。
誒。
我想誒提幾個問題，主席，我盡我時間提。
我一直對西九嘅建設咧，一直都關注。你好似Empress都好貴啦。
就算你而家係粵曲嗰個，大家都覺得好貴。好多藝術工作者將台灣、將日本、將好多經驗都講，點解要咁貴咧？咩啊？
咁都亦都睇到政府睇到西九，佢喺呢方面都想做翻啲嘢。
但落嚟嘅價錢係細嘅，就算而家黑鴿嗰度，你都話翻我哋聽係幾錢咧？
另外西九黑暗裏邊，可唔可以呢個建設過程當中一六一七實施嘅有嘅時候咧，之前做啲嘢咧，而家成好多文化界，我琴日先同一啲人傾緊，佢哋好關心就話能否喺你哋未好前咧做啲臨時黑盒咧？我問咗好多啲一啲即係出邊民間嘅，佢覺得真係西。
夠喐下嘢啦，唔好等到一七年先喐啦。你趁而家晒陽嘅時候，係咪做啲嘢咧？就等於我做華麗先，我都係做騰龍，開得一樣情況啫嘛，一樣可以做嘅。
咁所以，我覺得係咪呢方面靈活啲咧？一個就係價錢貴，第二個就喺而家呢個過渡期咧，能否有有啲臨時黑盒咧，擺翻喺黑盒嘅附近？我哋嗰日同阿阿阿Bonny佢哋傾嘅時候咧，同政府傾嘅時候咧，我哋都好刻意提咗呢個問題出嚟。
我覺得呢個係一個重要嘅。
即係剛才第一個問題，貴。
我諗合幾錢？第二個，你等等我講埋先啦。第二個咧，就覺得係咪可以做一啲喺臨時嘅時做啲嘢咧？
另外咧，我就想提有關副禮咧，我就畀個準則嗱，誒主席，我就唔想講逐點講，我覺得咧，二松唔好太嚴。
例如有啲地方自由嘢嘅度，地方係咪可以撥啲地方畀人哋擺啲攤檔買嘢咧？
我點解咁講咧？主席，我對個副例，我就對康文署係好有印象嘅。
佢咩用個管管管管管，就管到死曬。你知唔知？佢出邊嗰啲拍電影或者文化工作者好真康文處，你唔畀佢入邊影相，唔畀佢做啲拍啲小電影，唔得㗎喎。咁變咗你今情況，如果用康文處，當然剛才講就話唔係，我哋會要求更加寬嘅。我就覺得嗱，呢個你個尺度點咧？
我好擔心，如果你以康文處就係今日坐喺選民政局啲人咧，佢一定用管嘅角度。嗱，呢個一直係文化界同社會上啲誒設計嘅朋友一直批評政府啊，呢點我就希望。
將來嚟立法會，我諗呢點會認攻你哋嘅，即係你冇道理，人哋嚟拍片搞到嚴到好緊要，等於最後就話啊，我鬆咗之後都容易好嚴，呢個我我想提。
另外咧，我亦都想提一個問題，就係話誒，我希望政府喺你個人當中咧。
你有啲地方咁大，好似嗰個苗圃嗰個，係咪？我我就覺得唔好太多人為嘅噉嘅規劃。我幾欣賞我哋天馬林嗰度，唯一個樹唔夠啫，畀啲草定訓喺樹咯，唔好咁多幹預。實香港要啲環境咁呢個咧，我連問幾問題，唔該主席。好啊，誒。
係柯文全，唔係啊啊啊，馮太係咪？或者我諗大部分問題可能都要交翻畀管理局去答啦，即係關於嗰個造價等等。不過即係誒頭先啊陳議員提到咧，就係誒個扶例，其實頭先啊柏先生去介紹嘅時候咧，佢都多次去強調咧誒西九第日個公園咧。
同埋公共空間咧，係會用一套唔好唔同嘅方法嚟到去管理嘅。佢亦都唔係佢有參考，但係佢唔係去參抄曬康文署而家嗰套嘅管理方法，因為康文署佢係受一三二章嗰個嘅遊樂場條例去規管啦。咁呢個條例大家都知道係好幾十年前去寫落嚟，係有好多嘅誒，用一個比較。
管制嘅思維咧，嚟到係去做即係嗰個嗰個條例嘅。咁但係因為而家西九咧講緊係一個場地啦，我我自己從民政部嘅角度嚟睇咧，我哋覺得絕對係有嗰個空間咧，係去畀西九去實驗好多喺香港而家其他公園做唔到嘅嘢。咁如果將來如果西九呢一個場地係成功嘅咧，亦都可以帶翻一個經驗咧。
畀翻康文署咧，係去考慮係用喺喺佢哋嘅場地嗰度。我覺得呢一個絕對係一個互動嘅過程。咁誒，我我希望陳議議員明白咧，而家西九呢一套嘅附例咧，係同康文署嗰套嘅誒管理嘅方法係相當之唔同嘅。噉我或者誒其他嘅都交翻畀管理局去回答。好啊，阿Mr林誒，我諗。
時間唔係好夠，用一分鐘，你補充好啦，一分鐘。
Thanks, Mr. Chairman. Thanks for your good wishes. In regard to the cost issue, the cost issue of the black box, which is about to go out to tender, is approximately three hundred million Hong Kong dollars. Construction will commence later this year as part of the park.
We don't, because of the work that is going on on the site and the areas of the site that we don't have available to us, we don't have provision or budget for being able to provide temporary facilities. We'll be focused on the delivery of the black box, the outdoor stage and the art pavilion and the other buildings over the course.
of the two years up until completion of the park in 2017, and the four hectares of the temporary park are meant to provide ongoing access to the site through the building projects that will be taking part in the rest of the park. I think they're the key issue.
O.K. Thank you啊！我諗集中講翻我哋扶例先，好嘛？下一位，毛辦證。
我感謝Mr. Lynch for serving Hong Kong and this mammoth project.
And I hope it's all true that you were not, you haven't been invited to depart.
Now to come back to our bylaw.
excuse me。
continue。
啊，sorry。
I go on, continue, right? To go back to our bylaw discussions, I'm particularly concerned about about our street performance regulations that are coming up. How would you describe the the sort of what you have just now?
more lenient or at least less stringent.
rules to be conducted in the park and.
When an artist would like to come into the stage of performance, what sort exactly are your screening, vetting or for that matter censorship procedure?
That's my question number one. And question number two, your park management. I understand you're going to have your own staff, your own security.
deployment。
How's that going to happen? You are going to hire a lot of security guards and they they will be in uniform and.
things like this, you said you try to make public open space as free as possible, but then your staff will have the right to invite anyone to leave. Now that's going to be quite
controversal.
spot， I should think， I mean depends on how you judge a person's behaviour is disruptive or whatever， contravening any regulation， right？ And my third question is about you're allowing domestic pets inside。 Of course， I welcome
噉，
Chinese version it actually says domestic, well sort of kept animals. Well, that would include animal racing.
farming，所以係 Quite ridiculous. Thank you.
Okay.
The last one, I think tigers and lions would not qualify. We're not domestic, that's for sure. But no, we're looking clearly at trying to provide a response to the fact that Hong Kongers want places to take their domestic animals. They turn to be some of them might be birds. We don't think chicken.
Probably are going to be there, other than in the restaurants. And just going back to the other question before I hand over to Duncan to pick up the street performers issue, we've clearly made it one of the principles on which we're doing this is that we have to have responsibility to manage it and to make.
Sure, it's safe, but that we're not interested no in in trying to restrict people's activity. But like most parks in nearly every place I've worked or in any other part of the world, the people with responsibility for it have to have some powers to be able to exercise if people are.
irritating other people or upsetting other people or endangering other people, you know it's a light hand that we're proposing, but you know from our point of view we think that's going to work. I'll hand over to Duncan just to make a couple of other comments.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Just to pick up on that question about employing staff, it will be a mix of our own staff and of course contract staff. We wouldn't want to have huge numbers of our own staff; the cost would be prohibitive. Plus, there are advantages in having contract staff to carry out some functions. However, all of
Those staff doesn't matter whether it's contract staff or our own staff must be trained to our standards, and we will have a proper training regime in place to to make sure that they follow our requirements. The second question in in respect of that is, I wouldn't expect to see huge numbers of of people in
Formal uniforms. We want this to, from the start, from the very first impression, to be identifiable as members of the staff, but not necessarily wearing peaked caps and white shirts. It wouldn't be practical in the park. So we're looking at these details as we talk. In terms of vetting, I don't see it as vetting street performers. I really see it.
啊！
Making sure that when someone comes in and they claim to be able to juggle, they can juggle. Okay. Simple as that. It's very basic. If they claim to be able to juggle with flaming torches, I want to know that they can do so safely and in a manner that isn't going to cause damage to members of the public.
That's basically as as much as we will be doing at that initial stage. Can they do what they claim they are able to do? Simple, and it won't be very onerous.
The second level, which is a far more important area, is if someone has a special expertise.
some form of you know a multiple group.
type performance，then we would want to know that they may want to develop their capability and we can help them to do that. So it's a two-tier system. The very first tier is very simple， very basic and it just says， yes， this person juggles.
The next person who comes on may play the bagpipes, for example, which I would personally not like. Never mind. Okay, thank you, thank you, Mister. Okay, please go.
誒何秀蘭。
主席，誒我我會監察啊，Dr. Michael林取到最後一分鐘嘅。誒呢個附例係我哋傾咗好耐，誒即係攞到出嚟嘅。但係我想問一問佢喺嗰個法律地位上邊？第一咧同嘅。
你文件第十段嗰度講咧，就話香港現行規管公眾地方嘅法例會同樣適用於西九文化區。咁香港咧就有一條公眾娛樂場所條例，就傻到不得了嘅，連誒香港大學嘅演講廳都係入於公眾娛樂嘅活動。噉嘅當佢用。
用一條咁緊嘅法例去規管公眾地方活動，又可用可不用，又可以選擇性檢控，攞嚟告資聯會喺時代廣場擺呢個民主女神像嘅時候，究竟呢個西九文化區裏邊係？
咪。
即係要受呢條法例規管咧，定抑或係你嗰個附例係會即係更加即係有一個有一個我哋叫做就overriding effect咧？噉我相信係唔係嘅，即係可以請嘅今日有冇法律顧問咧去解一解畀我哋聽。另外咧就係誒嗰個。
附例嗰個草稿咧，其實係有一個，即係有兩個地方一定要提出嚟，定係講嘅。第一咧，佢就冇好似主體法例咁咧，有一個誒整體嘅正面積極嘅責任畀佢，因為喺主體法例裏邊咧，我哋即係嗰陣時做呢個主體法例咧一。
開始就話西九文化管理局係有以下嘅一係列職能。
咁誒，我當然希望咧，一係列職能咧係包括經社民公約裏邊，每人平等享有文化活動嘅權利。噉，我覺得呢啲正面積極嘅誒職責寫埋落去條附例嗰度咧，係畀你一連串嘅禁止呢樣禁止嗰樣咧，係更加好，因為有。
好多細節咧，你執行嘅時候，其實係有好多灰色地帶。即係如果你係好似特區政府而家噉樣。
揾方便自己嘅法例去執行咧，係可以仍然打壓得好緊要。噉我哋必須係有一啲正面積極嘅權利寫埋喺度咧，先正可以平衡得到嗱。我攞一啲例子出嚟啊，譬如好似誒誒抌垃圾咁嗰個liter嗰個字喺你附例嘅誒。
誒第三部嘅第四條咧，呢個器物咧就係可以指土壤灰塵。咁如果你有個公園喺度，通地都係土壤㗎啦，仲有落葉枯草。咁如果有個細路哥拎起塊即係枯葉，或者係玩泥沙，即係拎起扎泥沙，即係再再撒一撒。
嘅時候其實係中咗你個㗎啦，咁當然即係有常識嘅人、有邏輯嘅人咧，都唔會認為呢個細佬哥係犯咗法嘅。但係內行，我哋呢個政府而家係冇乜邏輯可講㗎嘛。噉你究竟？
即係呢啲法例啊，誒，公眾娛樂場所條例啊，同埋你嗰個主體法例，西九管理局主體法例之間，即係究竟邊個係有一個overriding effect咧？即係到時大家執行嘅時候又點樣咧？另外咧，我見到誒，你喺最尾嗰度咧，呢個誒。
草稿附例草稿最尾嘅第十步呢個執行及處罰嗰度咧，第六條咧你就誒，我相信你係用呢個第六A B咧就解決咗上次阿陶錦新議員提出嚟執法嗰個問題啦，就係話誒，你哋獲授權嘅人咧就可以將佢交畀警處，並且咧。
咧喺定警員嚟到之前可以扣留呢個人，呢個包唔包括使用武力嘅咧？即係如果包括嘅話，嗱唔包括你未必扣扣留到；包括嘅話，你有冇使用武力嗰個指引準則？
會唔會好過分啊？唔該，主席。好啊，請大家答邊位？誒，啊，Mr. Pascal， use one minute。
I think that there are two points I really want to make here. First, the
application of the.
pleasure ground.
Regulations under Section 109 of the Public and Municipal Services Ordinance will not apply.
Because we will not be gazetted as a as a public pleasure ground as such, that's why we have to have our own bylaws, which will be governing the provisions within the space controlled by the West Kowloon Cultural District Authority. Of course, other regulations under Cap One will apply because they apply throughout Hong Kong, but specifically.
The bylaws will apply only within this area, just as we wouldn't expect our bylaws to extend beyond our boundary.
Bad laws which apply apply under the Municipal Services Ordinance don't apply in inside our our area, so that's the first point. I think the second point is that common sense.
must apply at all times in the administration of rules.
governing the operation and management of this park. Of course, if a child is playing in a bunch of leaves, there's no way any of my staff would be expected to take action against that. It would certainly be considered to be unenforceable if you were to take it forward in that manner.
That's why I stress so much when I did my introduction on the training of the staff, so that they understand not just the letter of the law, but the spirit under which we want this site to be administered. And the spirit is to ensure that people can use it as freely as is practically and safely possible. And I keep coming back to this issue.
the measure, the test that we will always apply is: is it safe to do so?
If someone is climbing a tree and has reached 30 metres above ground, it's not safe.
We will take action if they're climbing in a in a short tree which is five or six metres above ground. We have to think about it. If they're climbing in a tree and damaging the tree, we'll take action. So it's got to be this measure of common sense and safety that we apply throughout. I think that's the most important approach.
噉我諗誒答唔曬啲第二輪啦，係咪？
跟住落嚟，陳子馳。
多謝主席。呢一個西九文化區嘅公園咧，無論最後起得幾靚都好咧。我覺得個主要嘅使命都係推廣文化。咁其中一個好重要，大家好關心就係關於街頭表演。我睇政府嘅文件第十五段啦，關於街頭表演第一句咧就話：街頭表演是成。
城市文化生活嘅重要部分。
噉我希望呢句説話唔單止係西九文化區公園嘅信念，亦都係成個特區政府嘅信念。但係我哋睇翻過去，我就唔覺得我哋嘅政府咧係信任呢一句街頭表演係城市文化生活嘅重要部分。咁今次西九文化區嘅公園，我覺得。
去嘗試去行呢一個街頭表演許可證呢個機制咧。如果佢能夠成功咧，可以借鏡翻畀誒民政事務局用嚟去發展一套真係街頭表演嘅政策嚇，即係呢個係一個好好嘅機會嚟嘅。所以針對翻今次呢一個街頭表演嘅許可證。
系統我都有啲意見同埋啲問題啦。其實街頭表演嘅管理係非常之重要，做得好同做得唔好，即係趕客定係鼓勵多啲人參與啦。咁今次我睇呢個指引咧，雖然頭先誒。
白生就話會係好寬鬆啦，但係我睇到個指引其實咧都唔係好寬鬆，有啲都幾幾嚴苛嘅。嗯，嗱個指引大部分寫都係對於唔同自憤者嘅態度嘅期望，即係希望大家以和為貴啊，可以協商到啊呢啲。咁但係譬如去到一啲實際嘅內，
內容表演者誒唔可以主動索取打賞啦，亦都唔應該幹預路過嘅途人啦。誒，所有表演者都要有嗰個許可證啦。即係譬如，如果有啲街頭表演係互動嘅，即係會請誒啲市民觀眾一齊參與表演嘅，咁可能就已經犯咗呢個規則啦。
咁如果你要有動物表演咧，即係譬如你馬騮戲啊噉樣咧，你要成為咗西九文化區街頭表演者計劃成員，即係個門檻好高喎，即係要攞到個十年嗰個即係。
許可證咁先至可以做到。如果唔係咧，一經規犯咧，就可以登記被吊銷，管理局將不會再發出新嘅許可證。咁呢個又係好重嘅，即係成世唔發啦，定係呢你個年期之內唔發啦噉樣。咁關於嗰個誒運作上咧，我嘅意見或者。
問題就係會唔會有限額嘅咧？呢一啲誒街頭表演許可證，抑或佢係誒來者不拒？
最低門檻啦，佢交咗個五分鐘嘅畀你，你睇過係嗰啲，跟住咧就儲咗一個pool喺度，到時每日去用咧，大家就鬥早去霸位啦噉樣。
定係會有配額嘅咧，即係譬如誒息時風太多噉啊，二户嗰啲可能咧就即係早啲就可能有個優先啊，係先到先得啊，定係抽籤咧？同埋我哋都會建議有臨時許可證誒，但遲容易啲申請或者可以即刻申請，甚或至有啲區域咧係唔需要許可證。
畀一啲誒外國人啦，佢哋嚟到嘅參與呢個演出，呢個又可唔可以考慮咧？好啊，邊位答？
Mr.Persaud。
First of all, I think this this this issue of compatibility. If we have someone that stands in the same place for eight hours playing the same song, there's going to be a problem.
people passing by will complain if they're right next to a restaurant, they're going to complain. We have to have the ability to control.
that sort of situation and it does happen. We've we've understood this from our research overseas that there have been instances of conflict caused by the fact that one performer just does one thing all the time. This is why we've said, look, maximum two hours restrictions on things like.
use of amplification equipment and so on and so forth, because it comes back to if you look at the guidelines that we put attached to the paper, we're trying to make sure that people are using a common sense approach that they don't overwhelm the situation by putting just one one type of activity.
however。
Our approach in terms of access is a minimalist approach. In other words, as I said before, can you do what you claim to be able to do? That's the first test.
The use of individual sites within the West Kalim Cultural District is the next stage in the process. We will have sites that are considered to be priority and high-profile sites where buskers would expect to be able to perhaps raise money through, you know, their performance. We will have to control access to those, but we want to do it on a fair and equitable basis.
and that's what we're developing these guidelines to do because we want to work with the performers to understand a system that they can accept and that works for them. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
O.K.
主席，佢答啲都係好概念嘢，我覺得好實際嘅，好嘛？第二輪，第二輪。
下一位副主席。
誒，多謝主席。首先咧，我係即係肯定呢一個誒，而家草案中嘅嗰個扶例咧，嗰個誒。
草擬嘅方式啦，咁呢個即係如果你話係誒。
唔受嗰個公眾遊樂場地嗰個掣肘咧，咁呢個已經係一大嘅。
進步啊！
噉我亦都誒覺得咧，你係寫嘅時候咧，係以反映。
嗰個西九成個計劃嗰個願景同埋使命咧，呢個係正確嘅方向。但係我想問一問咧，就係。
誒呢個願景，即係話製造令香港引以為傲嘅優質綠化户外空間，同埋嗰個使命，即係成為啟發推動同埋鼓勵文化活動嘅海濱公園。
呢兩樣嘢咧，其實都喺而家草案嘅附例之中咧，係冇出現到嘅。
咁誒，我想聽聽，或者主要講都係柏志高先生啦，係咪？即係你哋係點樣諗嘅？即係呢個願景同埋使命，點樣喺呢一個誒負例嘅貫徹落實同埋執行嘅時候咧，係可以真係？
發揮得到作用，而有別於而家康文署所管理嘅嗰啲誒。
公眾遊樂場地啦，咁因為你執行嘅時候，你要主導。
嗰個。
誒執行嘅咧，應該就係願景同埋使命啊嘛。咁而你去到真係前線嘅時候啊，或者你決定點樣去對於某一類持份者去定限制咧，嗰種取捨拿捏之間咧，都係應該係貫徹嗰個願景。
同埋使命嘅，噉我想問下嗰個諗法係點？譬如譬如，你會唔會將呢個使命同埋願景真係入咗條例裏邊咧？即係直情有一個有一個條款係講明嗰個願景同埋使命，即係一個叫做mission statement或者。
一個vision statement噉樣嚇，寫咗落去。
甚至咧，你會唔會話即係喺執行嘅時候咧？如果要去到一個取捨拿捏之間嘅時候，誒，你係會誒以呢個願景同埋使命作為嗰個誒？
即係基礎啊！任何執行方法係有違使命同原則嘅，都應該係被啊！
即係取替嘅噉，即係我想聽清楚，知點樣將呢一樣嘢係去落實嘅。
我。
Mr. Pesco, thank you, Mr. Chairman. In fact, the members quite rightly point out one of the dilemmas that we have.
The law has to be written legally. It has to conform with the drafting standards of writing law that the legislative council can pass.
When we started this process, we were we were trying to do exactly what.
The honourable member has suggested, in other words, put in some sort of statement of intent within the law. But there isn't a provision that we could do that naturally, so we've taken a different approach and put those statements into the into the guidelines. So, for example, just to quote.
the first the street performance guidelines we actually start with a statement the West Kalim Cultural District exists to promote appreciation and participation in the arts we strive to support the creation composition production learning and practice of arts and culture so we're trying to get these messages in the into the way we will administer and manage the site
But we have to be consistent with the law, so that's the way we're trying to do it. But we absolutely accept that in doing so, the vision mission must be at the heart of what we're trying to do, and the guidelines are written with that very firmly in mind.
Thank you. OK。跟一跟一就係喺誒起草嗰個誒附例嗰陣時候咧，有冇尋求過即係法律意見？有冇可能係將嗰個願景同埋使命咧，係用某一種方式係入法咧？
Mr. Chairman, yes, we did seek legal advice on this, and of course we've had help with the drafting. It has been submitted to the Department of Justice, for example. They've got to vet it, make sure it's compliant with the requirements. So yes, that's already been carried out.
O.K.第一輪仲有冇人提問？
啊啊啊！彭太。
誒，因為即係我哋立法嘅誒，亦都有一套convention啦。咁誒，通常咧，我哋所謂vision mission statement咧，就好少寫落去個法例裏邊。誒，正如頭先阿柏生講，寫喺個guidelines或者寫喺西九自己嗰個即係整體嗰個誒，我哋叫V M V咧，就比較係適合嘅。
OK。
再第一輪再冇人提問，如果冇咧，我都想問幾個問題咧。就係我想問啊，即係啊啊馮太咧，依個附例咧，會唔會再拎上立法會？係係佢係好似其他嘅附例咁過一過咧，係咪？第二點咧，雖然頭先啊柏兆高答覆啊副主席都講得話，好多字眼都要firm啲。
啊，好要要要實在一啲，但係我又睇到有啲字眼咧，我都唔知模稜兩可喎，譬如痕黑。
點樣叫行黑咧？
好而家好多啲街頭藝術家咧，佢一路表演咧，一路擺個擺個夾喺度，打開佢噉，你係抌錢落去噉，呢啲算唔算行黑？第二，如果就算唔係，佢又自己自制幾隻C D噉樣擺喺度，你畀你買嚇咁咁呢個係算係商業行為，抑或係行行黑咧？呢兩樣嘢係。
咪都唔準咧。咁第一點，第二點咧，你喺度講攝影啦。我因為我都好中意攝影。噉你攝影咧，點樣叫做商業攝影咧？啊，譬如話啊，我女要影翻婚紗，我帶曬成套架撐噉樣去嗰度影婚紗啊。咁咁點樣去detect翻去證明佢係商業定係唔商業咧？
係嘛？噉你有咩準則依依樣嘢咧？第二而家就好興啲微電影啊、短片啲拍攝啦，即係民政局都好推廣呢啲嘢啦。咁咁譬如有一班人咁喺度拍拍電影，叫做微電影或者係短片，噉你點知佢係商業定唔商業咧？噉樣或者你點樣去？
去衡量咧嚇，可唔可以講講？嚇，或者我先答咗第一條題目啦，就誒呢一個嘅附例咧，係需要經過立法會以先審議後定立嘅形式嚟到通過嘅，即係positive voting，係誒唔係即係二十一加二十八嗰種係需要即係真係一個正式嘅審議嘅程序嘅。噉我哋而家預算咧會喺誒最
快希望第二季可以拎翻翻嚟咧，立法會呢度係畀誒立法會去審議。
Mr. Peskov, dealing with your other two points, if I can refer you to the guidelines on page three in the English version, at least, we specifically deal with this issue of raising money in commercial activities as a part of a busking activity. And the logic here is, if people are trying to market something that
They have created themselves, be it a song or a model or an artwork, then that's acceptable. But if they are trying to hawk or sell products from a variety of different places, that becomes prohibited activity unless it's authorised. So it's a very clear distinction, and we have addressed that in the guidelines.
都係冇銀紙睇到，都係you cannot show anybody trading。
You can you can for example if someone has is a saxophone player and they have a CD of them playing a saxophone they can sell that CD because it's something they've created themselves. But if they're selling world famous saxophone players from the US and Australia, that is not acceptable. It's that distinction.
That's okay. To answer your second question about commercial filming and specifically wedding photography, and I'm glad you raised that because it is an issue. We do not want to interfere with people taking photographs of weddings. That, of course, is going to happen, and we won't have any view on that. But if a company
regularly uses our venue for filming of weddings. From a professional point of view, we will have a look at that, and of course we would expect them to register and get approval for that. Not necessarily because it's a problem, but it's because they're using space within the park which could otherwise be used by members of the public, and I think that's the important issue.
但。
這些係啲啲 sort of refinements in our approach that we will be looking at to encourage people to use the park for the for casual photography. Absolutely, but it's when it becomes professional. And as as many members will be aware, wedding photography in Hong Kong is big business. They bring a lot of equipment, including.
makeup including screens and backdrops and what have you. That's the sort of activity that we need to look at very carefully. And Mr. Chairman, I guess the other issue would be. I think one's acquainted with those big moony weddings of twenty, ten thousand people. They're the sorts of
events that we would have to control. If you know people decide that they want to get 10,000 people married on the site, they'd only be able to do that with permission, and I suggest that's probably unlikely to to be available as an option because it would completely disrupt you know the rest of the public's use of the park.
不過我我諗你都要考慮下咯，有好多時影結婚照就算業餘嘅咧，佢都係帶埋帶齊反光板啊，多一兩個人幫手做下make up啊，做下。No problem, Mr. Chairman. No problem. For you or your daughter.
O.K.誒，你哋翻去諗清楚啦，我攞咗時間啦。請下劉慧卿議員。誒誒，多謝主席，唔好意思啊，遲咗啲啊，主席嚇。不過咧就誒，我我都想問下咧，即係誒嗱，而家咧呢個係會翻嚟立法會審議㗎，係咪啊？咁到時我哋都應該要做啲公眾諮詢啦。咁如
如果當即係你哋大家覺得你哋已經做得好足夠咧，噉啊諮詢嗰陣時就唔會有太多意見嘅。咁但係如果你哋係即係唔聽人講咧，噉我哋做諮詢嘅時候咧就個個走曬嚟嘅。好似隔離房啊，而家講緊三跑啊，嚇議員都嘈到拆天啊嚇。咁第日一公用諮詢咧就去大球場諮詢先得啊，主席。
嚇，好好啊！咁所以呢個係嗱，咁其實你哋而家有啲做法咧，係同康文處咧係有出入嘅，主席嚇。噉啊啊啊，秘書長都喺度啦，你都知啦嚇。咁其實康文處有啲做法咧，就有議員同埋有公眾咧，就即係唔係好接受嘅。咁但係點樣去？
改革康民署就唔係我哋今日要講嘅議題啦。但係如果做到出嚟喺呢度係好嘅，咁希望政府都會接受就推廣去其他你哋管嘅公園啊、場地啦。咁所以咧，我係誒即係我係嗱，我係好贊成係開放啊，畀市民嚟去用，但係都要有啲秩序啦。
同埋有啲情況，有啲其他公園咧就嘈到好緊要嘅，有啲人喺度唱歌啊嗰啲咧，搞咗好多年都搞唔掂嘅嚇。咁同埋就即係嗰個地方嘅清潔咧，我亦都覺得係好緊要嘅。即係我嘅問題就係我哋點樣去揾幾樣嘢去揾揾到個平衡？誒，同埋你話。
畀啲動物入去，噉我都好贊成。而家都越嚟越多動物公園啦，咁啲市民就即係好緊張佢啲寵物。咁但係佢嚟到嘅時候，點樣要控制住，又可以玩得開心，又唔會滋擾其他人，又唔會整污糟啲地方咧。咁所以或者你簡單啲講一講，你點樣去去即係揾呢幾樣嘅。
平衡同埋咧，係咪即係第日就算係開咗咧，都應該有一個即係各界可以參與嘅諮詢委員會啊，乜都好，咁可以定期同你哋開會，畀啲意見你，抑或你係本身嘅有咩格有咩機制，去一路收集到意見，聽到即係有或者有啲咩改善。
嘅咧，唔該，主席。好啊，誒，邊個答啊？Mr. Mr.哥啊，You。
一 couple of things then.
cleanliness of the park. I think this is actually one of those management issues that we need to look at. Mr. Pascoe, can you please speak into the microphone? Otherwise, no one can hear you. The cleanliness of the park. It's a management issue that we need to look at. The
the the first logic is we we want to allow people to bring their their domestic animals, pets primarily, and food and drinks. Well, again, we're not going to restrict food and drink if people bring it themselves. But if they try to take up space, for example, for barbecuing a hangi or whatever, that would be restricted.
Because there are there are there are degrees of tolerance that we have to look at, and I gave an answer to an earlier question about common sense, and the key issue here will be the training of our staff to apply common sense in every context, as long as
The activity is not.
unsafe for other users. So, for example, if someone doesn't pick up.
After their dog or cat has made a mess, that's unsafe. That must be dealt with. But of course, as long as they look after the dog properly, then that would be acceptable. In terms of the consultative committee idea, this is something we are looking at. Of course, we already have a consultation panel within West Kalim Cultural District as one of the authorities.
channels through which we get advice from the public, and that contains a large cross section of different people from the community. And I'm certainly looking at perhaps having different interest groups within the park, because I think you know there'd be people who are interested in the flora and fauna, there'd be interested in the artworks, there'd be interested in the.
主席，我簡單講講，因為又你走去睇一啲郊野公園咧，以前都幾好嘅，而家好多人都同我投訴，就話覺得好污糟。即係一方面就話政府唔執得夠啦，但係有啲市民用嘅時候咧，都係比較慢。
麻煩，咁所以咧係幾樣嘢都要關顧。如果你去到個地方唔清潔啊，或者係好蠟好撈搞啊，噉係係好弊嘅。但係市民又想你係儘量係畀佢可以去使用嚇，唔好有咁多規範。咁所以係一個平衡嚟嘅。噉我覺得你持續有班人喺度畀意見你咧，呢個係要。
諗嘅，主席唔該。好，誒黃碧雲。
啊，主席，誒喺文件嗰度咧就講誒西九管理局喺草擬呢一個誒。
西九文化區嘅公園個扶例嘅時候咧，係有誒考慮到其他國家嗰個模式嘅，包括澳洲、加拿大、新加坡、南非、英國、美國、內地知名城市嘅公園嘅管理模式。咁但係咧就誒文件就冇清楚講咧，最後。
後，你哋其實係用咗邊個國家嘅模式，誒，或者係一個綜合嘅模式咧？咁誒，咩模式係適合香港？可唔可以簡單講一講？
OK。
It's a composite model taking into account best practice across many countries. We've looked closely at parks like Centennial Park, Central Park, Hyde Park, you know, in three different countries, and then we've looked at the rules and the regulations and the bylaws, and have come up with something that we think best.
Reflects some of the pressure points that have been raised by Legco over many years in regard to the park and the existing rules that on the on the LCSD parks in Hong Kong, and come up with something which we think is a a good addition to the way that it works for us.
是The body responsible, but it works for the people who are going to be using those parts.
O.K.慘碼一碟。噉啊，主席即係話冇一個特別嘅一個誒其他國家公園嘅模式係我哋而家用緊嘅，而係綜合地去採納。
係咪係咯？炒買跌啊嘛，都係一樣。啊，yes。
咁如果嗱，如果我哋唔係話真係抄邊一個國家模式，我想問咧嗱，因為你都有提到我哋有誒香港仲有海洋公園啊、迪士尼啊，或者其他康文署嘅公園嘅。咁呢三呢呢呢呢三個其他嘅即係管理嘅模式，又？
會同將來西九文化區誒嗰個嘅呢個公園個管理模式有咩唔同咧？What we have certainly looked at Disney Park, Ocean Park and the LCSD parks, but I think the
壓力，that come from the Ledco over all of the discussions was that this park needs to be different. And what Web tried to do is to pick up the very best practice, the best ideas we could find from other places. Recognising this is not like Ocean Park or Disney Park where you have to pay an entry fee. This is a park for every
Everyone to be made as accessible as possible. So the models for Ocean Park and Disney Park do not really provide us with the best examples, and we clearly have had lots of discussion with the Legco subcommittee on the L.C.S.D. parks. We've talked to L.C.S.D. We've talked to the community.
through the stages of public engagement to ensure that what we're coming up with is going to be broadly acceptable to the community, to the users, and to the people who have responsibility for actually running the park.
OK。
係啊，繼續。誒，我再想問一問咧，就係嗰個誒嗰個西九文化區嘅負例。
嗰度咧就係誒關於啊第六部公廁嗰部分。
咁咧，我唔知剛才有冇其他委員睇到。咁咧就呢個公廁又好重要，因為去到公園你唔會即刻出嚟。咁但係呢個公廁嗰度咧就誒完全冇提咧，就係誒第一就冇提嗰個殘疾嘅廁所啦。咁第二咧就係冇中性嘅誒廁所。
好啦，咁因為呢度咧，你一係就男廁，一係女廁，男嘅咧就唔準入女，女嘅唔準入男，然後咧唔可以帶異性細個五歲以下。咁如果五歲以上嗰啲點算咧？咁又或者有有親人要照顧佢，唔可以自己去如廁嘅。噉你嗰啲異性嗰啲點處理？有冇中性時間安排？
圖圖都有嘅嚇，Unisys都有嘅。
另外，另外，但係，Mr. Chenon， there will be disabled toilets which are not designated male or female, so they will be usable by people who need support and assistance.
I think we will not support the way of using the disabled toilet for those carer because they are not not all are disabled, right? Or they are disabled in different sense. So I think you will also jeopardise the need and right of those disabled person.
perhaps we can take this one offline and discuss it separately because I'm a little bit confused about the issue I'm afraid, Mr. Chairman.
The issue is that for those carer, they may have to take care of the relatives.
which is over the age of five and in opposite sex, and according to the draft of this ordinance, they will not be able to take care of them. Well, they will through the disabled toilets. Yeah, I mean, I mean, disabled toilet cannot be used as a care toilet. The concept is wrong. Sorry, that's exactly.
Exactly what a disabled toilet is. It's intended to allow people who need, who have disabilities that have more space, or who require assistance, to be given that assistance. That's exactly what the purpose is. Okay. 我諗咁咧，你都要留意下嗰啲 disabled toilet咧。 That as
As someone who is disabled, I think we've put a lot of effort into the idea of ensuring that the universal access
responsibilities are very clearly dealt with in both the design of the buildings and the design of the park, and that those issues are well covered in all the discussion that's taken place. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. All I all I require is that you plan to have some gender neutral toilet. 我聽到你嘅意見。
佢自己翻去諗啦，好嘛？時間就夠啦嚇。第二輪嘅咧就何秀蘭。係啊，唔該主席，我跟進翻頭先啊，副主席同我一齊都誒問過嗰個嗰個問題，就係要有一個mission statement擺喺度。其實呢個西九誒文化管理局嘅條例咧，裏邊就有呢個管理局嘅誒職能。
擺咗喺誒好前嘅地方，噉我希望咧呢條附例咧，起碼係會喺呢個長提啊，或者係喺某一度咧，就要講明呢呢個附例嘅實施係要嚟符合落實西九管理局嗰誒誒管理呢個文化區嘅職責。咁當然啦，就誒律政處係。
有更加多嘅專才喺度噉，我相信你哋一定係可以揾到一個辦法去誒寫低我哋誒議員嗰個誒關注嘅。第二咧，主席就係即係跟翻嗰個第六步嘅公廁嗰部分咧，其實即係時候要檢討下㗎啦。呢個即係公共廁所呢個。
呢個法例咧，就係。
即係跟即係香港其他嘅法例，咁其實誒除咗呢個誒誒跨性別人士啊或者照顧者冇處理到之外咧。
其實你你同香港嘅刑事條例咧，其實都有矛盾之處。嗱，第一個問題咧，反為比較容易解決，即係譬如好似啲商場裏邊咧，而家都有啲叫做家庭一齊共用嘅誒洗手間，噉你就可以畀佢入。咧太古廣場有㗎啦，過條馬路就會見到㗎啦。嗰個就即係一家人一齊入去嘅。
啊！所以就冇男女之分。咁另外咧，就係其實香港嗰個刑事罪行責任咧，兒童嗰個嗰個免責年齡咧已經提高到十歲㗎啦。但係你呢度咧嗰個闊面咧。
就就咁不適用於五歲以下，噉你睇一睇啦。五歲以下到十歲其實都唔係即係好知道啲嘢啱定唔啱，咁呢個亦都係本港法例裏邊一啲有即係自相矛盾嘅地方噉。但係呢啲細節我哋可以翻到去審議附例嘅時候咧，再提出嚟。噉我一個大方向去問咧，就係。
係嗰個街頭表演，其實我哋都會好擔心咧，會唔會重複即係西洋菜街嗰個情況？因為有啲街頭表演者咧，覺得即係發出好巨型嘅聲浪咧，係佢嘅權利嚟嘅。噉我見到你一個指引嗰度咧，就係誒都係叫佢哋誒互相忍讓啊，用啲小型電池。
啊！各樣嘢咁其實太小型嘅音響咧，出嚟就真係噪音，就唔係靚嘅音響。但係太大型咧，如果嗰嗰批表演團體佢自己唔識互相尊重，唔識尊重呢個場地咧。
你結果就係即係好可能重複西洋菜街嗰種情況。雖然即係西九係距離住宅，即係我希望都係比較遠啲咧，唔係好似西洋菜街嗰度嗰個情況咁惡劣啦。但係如果你淨係靠自律咧，就我都恐怕佢攞咗個牌照，即係個表演證之後咧就。
誒，即係太太。
即係爭取自己嗰個發出聲響嗰個權利。咁所以，我我睇你嗰個誒指引嗰度，你會唔會有一個取消即係表演證嘅誒條件喺度咧？
好，邊位答？啊，Mr. Peck。
I note the comments about the the family. We did actually look at the age. We had a big debate when we were looking at.
Where would be the appropriate cut off for children and other parents to go into? I think the first point is the toilets we're talking about are young children of one sex going into a toilet of the other sex. That's that's the issue here. We don't want to encourage that. We actually want to stop that because of various anti.
social behaviours that we know, there will be other toilets that are not specified as male toilets or female toilets where these people, if they need support, can go in. That I can assure you will be the case, just as I've said before. Now let me turn to this issue of antisocial behaviour within
busking and and street performances. Let me stress, we are not the same as Sai Ying Choi Street. We control the area. We have responsibility. The bylaw will give us the power to deal with those issues. I don't think that there would be an issue.
Having said that, of course we do need to be transparent in the way we manage administer this, and that's why the guidelines contain details such as the use of amplification equipment, duration and so on and so forth. Because we don't want to get into a dispute when we start, because people say, well, no, I didn't know what the rules were. That's why the guidelines are so.
所以，使人民知道。
They can come and ask us questions, and we can show them exactly what the rules will, and they will apply to everybody. They will be consistently applied throughout the district. And I think that's the most important aspect of what we're trying to do here. 好嘅，下一位誒陳志全。多謝主席。我係跟進翻頭先嗰組問題，我好簡單、好清楚咁問。
第一就係關於個許可證，許可證係咪申請咗佢就全年可以喺嗰個地方嗰度表演，係用誒先到先得去霸位就可以表演，定係會有另一個即係登記配額咧，每日噉樣。第二就係我對於話，如果要有寵物加入演出，要先成。
為西九文化區街頭表演者計劃，即係攞到呢個十年牌，我覺得個門檻係太高。我希望可以即係聽聽意見。第三就係關於一旦許可證被吊銷，管理局將不會再發出新嘅許可證嘅意思係乜嘢？第四就係可唔可以考慮臨時或者？
一啲誒單次短期嘅許可證，甚至係有區域唔需要許可證，畀一啲誒，例如我遊客啊，或者年青人學生嘅噉嘅表現咧。好啊，四個問題。
Let me deal with the quota and the animals thing first. There will be, as I said before, a number of spaces that we will designate as prime locations, which are intended to be sites which have a higher level of control. They may be adjacent to restaurants. They may be in, for example, the artist's square. Those we would have.
more regulation applying, but for other spaces within the park, we think that it's better to have a much less formal system than a quota system.
But we will apply the two hour rule. So if someone is is performing for two hours, and they exceed that performance, and someone else is waiting, then we would expect that person to move on, and they would be replaced. So there will be a turnover within all of the spaces. The other reason that we want that is that if they're adjacent to, for example, a kiosk.
what have you, we we don't want the conflict to build between one person who's constantly occupying a space and the kiosk operator or or other people. So we will have different levels depending on the location. I think that's quite important. Animals.
this is this is a difficult one. For example, if you have a someone who comes in to to be a snake charmer.
你 really do need to know what you're doing to be able to charm snakes.
Therefore, we would apply stricter rules on that sort of behaviour because of the potential risk to people.
monkeys you mentioned yourself monkeys can actually be quite difficult to manage if you're not familiar with their management that's why we must know what your performance is how the animal will be involved is it properly licensed is it properly looked after does for if it's a dog show do they have rabies shots etc we need to know about this.
and that's why we have a registration system which will apply to all performance. Third.
This issue of revoking the permit.
嗯。
The intention is that we work with people.
但係， at the end of the day， if someone cannot work with us and we can't work with them， we need to be able to take action。 otherwise， there is no sanction under the bylaw。 but the intention at all times will be to work with people to explain why the rules are there， to be transparent about the way we will administer them， so that we don't get into a situation where we have to。
But frankly, if at the end of the day we have to revoke, we will do so, because on the grounds of safety, on the on the grounds of human decency and all of the other issues that would normally apply in public space. In terms of short-term permits, it will depend. For example, I could envisage at some point in the future there being a
buskers festival。
people coming from all over the world as an event, and of course under an event situation, we would have a different set of rules and that would apply specifically to that event. But for regular every day of the week type operations, the permits would apply and they will be available for for the periods described in the guidelines. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
主席，主席，我想我個關於吊銷，我唔係反對佢管理局佢有權吊銷一個人嗰個許可證，但係我問係吊銷咗，咁不會再發出新嘅嘅意思係乜嘢啫？佢冇答到。可唔可以有個期間之內啊？食環署都有扣分，扣幾耐先又冇咗佢啊？
Mr. Chairman， we're looking at different forms of management， and we will obviously consider that。你都考慮下啦，你以前房屋處都係噉啊，過咗一年噉啊，clear咗佢啊。OK，下一個副主席。
主席，我我噉我都係想再跟一跟嗰個mission vision嗰度啦。啊，因為阿柏志高先生咧，其實可以翻去睇一睇咧呢個西九文化區管理局條例咧，其實第四條嘅括弧一同第四條嘅括弧二嘅。
嗱，佢四括弧二咧，我讀一讀個英文咧就係噉嘅。The authority shall perform its functions under subsection one in ways which aim to achieve the following objectives。
然後，它被列在第二節，從A到N，一些目標的WKCDA。
我係just wondering whether a similar
啊！
adaptation， or an adaptation similar to 4-2， could be included in the bylaws， for example， to say that the authority shall enforce these bylaws only in ways which aim to achieve the following mission and vision， something like that.
係。
或，perhaps you could consult your legal experts to see whether it is possible to introduce a preamble to the bylaws to reflect the mission and vision statements. That I think would
really be helpful, and that would also stand these bylaws apart from those.
啊，made。
under Chapter 132.
咁呢個只其一啦，或者啊柏少古先生可以一間答一答。但係我其實想再問一問咧，就係關於嗰個表演誒，佢表演嗰度咧，即係我其實咧就好歡迎咧，係有一個噉樣嘅機制咧，係畀人申請嗰個許可證嘅。咁但係，如果將主席
如果你將呢個誒街頭表演指引同嗰個舉辦户外節目指引比較一下咧，你就會發覺咧，後者咧，即係嗰個申請舉辦户外活動指引咧，係有一個叫申請程序嘅。咁嗰度咧就交代咗一個管理局會成立一個委員會，成員包括外界持。
違憲者等等嘅噉，同埋會徵詢委員會意見啦。我想問下誒西九管理局咧，其實關於嗰個街頭表演個申請程序係點㗎？係咪都會有一個委員會負責啊？即係冇理由次次都要交上去嗰個董事局啊，由政務司司長做主席嗰個嚟到嚟到決定發許。
可整㗎係嘛？好兩個問題，Mr. Peacock。嗯，Mr. Chairman, a couple of points. Um, I would love to write into our bylaws the vision, mission statement. I'll have a look at that, because honestly, it helps us. That's exactly what we're trying to do. So we'll have a look at it. But so far, we've not been able to come up with an appropriate wording. Um, so I can't promise that we'll be able to, but we'll certainly have a look at that.
On the the application procedure, no, the basic procedure will be very simple. No reference back to the board. We're making a distinction here between something that's
recurrent happening regularly, and something an event which happens occasionally or from time to time, particularly because an event will take up space. It will be either for hire or for occupation purposes. It will restrict access to the for the public to those spaces. So we need a different approach.
for events to these informal, as I would regard it, street performances. So it also coincides with our philosophy that we want to encourage street performances as far as we can, as long as they're done safely. So it's the safety angle that we're really looking at, and that's why we won't be referring to committees or what have you.
for the the basic permit, that's a very simple. Come along, our staff will see that you can juggle.
Go ahead.
好嘅，劉偉興。
阿主席啊，有幾樣我提一提嘅嗱，嗰個街頭表演嗰度咧，我覺得係其實好多人做嘅，咁所以你成個程序啊、點樣申請啊、點樣去誒，即係安排咧係好緊要，希望做得好暢順啦嚇。咁同埋嗰啲誒餐飲設施咧，我係好贊成嘅，但係點樣令到佢係？
誒，即係乾淨啦，同埋即係誒，好配合成個環境咯。因為如果唔係，你淨係齋坐咧，又唔係咁咁吸引啦。但係你又唔可以太多㗎嘛，就即係希望係樣樣都要點樣去拿律拿捏，同埋喺公園裏邊希望有多啲凳啦嚇，可以畀人坐，就唔係一坐就要坐喺草地或者咩。
咁個廁所嗰度咧，我希望咧，尤其是女廁，一定個廁隔咧係要足夠，因為我睇到有幾個廁所啊，但係就唔好即係多好多人去到公園嘅時候，個個要排曬大隊啊，噉啊真係好煩啦。咁關於攝影嗰度咧，主席啊，因為有陣時咧，我哋會喺你哋嗰啲誒康文處啲嗰啲地方嗰度做。
訪問啦，記者攞個電視機嚟，咁啲人係唔畀嘅。嗱，嗰個其實唔係，當然個電視台而家係商業啦，但係你做嗰啲嗰啲唔係我哋收錢嘅嘢嚟㗎嘛。咁嗰個係咪都係嚴得咁緊要嘅咧？或者你都解釋一下。O K，邊位解釋？係。
阿馮達。
係多謝啊，劉議員嘅提問。誒，就住嗰個嘅誒訪問咧，其實誒新聞處同埋將來西九嘅做法都會係一樣嘅。如果係新聞嘅報道採訪咧，係唔需事先申請嘅。咁個別情況可能誒有一啲嘅，我哋都知道前線嘅誒保安人員咧，佢可能係唔瞭解。如果係即係一啲商業。
嘅攝影咧係需要事先申請，呢個係康文署同西九將來個做法都會係一樣嗰度，或者澄清翻嗰個原則啊。
嗰啲街頭表演嗰個係咪真係有有啲比較細節嘅規矩去拿捏？大家又覺得公道，亦都可以處理到。如果唔係，就係你好多紛爭啊。Okay，回應下，Mr. Besco。Maybe I can ask just to to confirm. Um, news reporting no there's no rules applying to news reporting. I think that's an important principle. Let me go back to
Female toilets. In fact, the park designers, you can have a look there, have been specifically asked to make sure we have enough toilets within the park within a reasonable distance. And I touched on that in the presentation earlier because we understand that issue. So, for example, the toilets that will be adjacent to the black box will be available for the.
public to supplement the regular toilets elsewhere within the park. So we we're looking at that as a specific issue. And I thank member for that comment. In terms of the catering facilities, one of the ideas that we're looking at again, I touched on it in the presentation, is removable.
椅子和和桌子。如果你去到一些公園在歐洲和美國，他們有。
Like temporary chairs that people can move around to set up for themselves, we think that would be a really nice feature in this park. And so that's one of the things that we're looking at, and we'll try that out in the nursery park to see if it works. If it does, then we can transfer that into the the main park in due course. In terms of the procedures.
for street performance. That's why we're putting together the guidelines. And let me stress, we are actually working with the street performers as well, so that they understand what we're trying to achieve. We've had some discussions with representative groups already. We're engaging them in this process so that they can understand exactly how we will administer it and the requirements.
But let me stress, the basic entry requirement is very simple. It's just can you do what you claim to do? So if you if you claim to be a saxophone player, can you actually play the saxophone?
That's that's as simple as a, it'll be a two or three minute performance in front of one of our staff who over time will gain experience in in assessing what is is an ability to do something or not. This is not about the quality. Quality is the second stage where we're trying to enhance the performance standards. Just just one quick.
How do you ensure that there will not be too many street performers performing at the same time? Exactly. Well, this is this is where we're looking at designating sites within the area where we believe street performances could take place without causing problems, and we're using that as the concept within locations so that there aren't too many.
conflicts between straight performers. Plus, there will be a distance, a spacing requirement between performers, and that will also be set out in the guidelines. So, if they reach a certain number, the others cannot go in to perform. They'll have to wait until the next changeover in two hours, because as we've said,我會做一個機制之後再畀大家研究下啦。依度我再。
佢有一個regulation，佢自己做好啲，係嘛？翻去黃碧雲。
誒主席就我希望頭即係頭先講嘅廁所女廁嗰度咧，即係西九管理局都要留意。我哋而家都推動立法會裏邊會有相關法例嘅修訂，要增加女廁資格嗰個比例嘅。噉我哋希望就係男廁資格加尿兜嘅數目，相對於女性資格嘅數目咧，唔會。
會少過一比二噉，所以如果你係跟現有嘅法例咧，到你起好公園嘅時候就過時㗎啦，因為我哋立法會都會改呢條法例嘅。
咁跟住，我想問咧，就係關於我睇完呢條誒條例咧，似乎完全冇講啊吸煙區同埋非吸煙區嘅安排嘅。
噉就而家我哋香港有法例就禁止即係室內好多食肆嗰啲禁止吸煙。但係如果你作為呢一個成個西九嘅區域有咁多誒表演嘅街道啊、公園嗱，你一定喺附例裏邊，我唔知點解你有呢一個omission，即係完全冇提誒嗱。我哋。
車咧已經係放曬喺地底㗎啦，因為上個公園啊，成個文化區咧係有清新嘅空氣。咁但係點解吸煙呢度完全提都冇提嘅咧？嗱，其實我哋而家收到好多居民投訴咧，就係話佢哋啊，反而喺餐廳度冇事，但係一行出街，哇，成條街好多人企曬喺門口嗰度。
即係誒食煙嘅，噉佢喺度等位咧，喺出邊咧都都喺度焗住吸二手煙。嗱，咁而家西九文化區究竟嗰個安排，你係會全面禁煙啦，定係乜乜嘢咧？噉我睇唔到你呢條條例喺禁止行為嗰度第十二段第四步係完全冇，你話不準生火，我唔知你生火算唔算？
係吸煙，噉我諗你唔係啦嚇，咁所以我估你應該要考慮加翻，即係誒，我哋我諗我哋要一個方法係確保嗰個即係公園同埋西九文化區係一個即係誒，即係空氣清新同埋唔會被逼吸入二手煙。噉你嗰個做法咧，我覺得你係咪應該考慮下，譬如。
大阪噉啊，Osaka，佢哋喺街道上邊或者人口密集嘅地方，佢係禁止吸煙嘅，全部好多即係誒唔準吸煙嘅嘅sign，仲有一啲係執行呢一啲禁煙嘅警察，佢手裏邊係帶住一個便攜嘅煙灰缸，跟住咧要捉。
嗰啲人嘅噉，當然即係問題就係話你係誒喺禁止吸煙之餘，你要劃定一啲區域係可以畀佢吸煙啊。即係我哋去平衡誒嗰啲吸煙者同非吸煙者嗰個權益。噉你你而家呢度全部冇，噉我希望你解釋一下點解會冇咧？你個構思係諗住飲。
佢哋點樣都都得咧噉。好嘛，解釋兩個名。
Clause eleven F, we of the actual bylaw, we say that there will be no smoking or bringing of cigarettes or pipes or other smoking paraphernalia unless it is in a specified smoking area. I guess our intention is that this is.
是 meant to be as eco-friendly as possible, so we've specifically dealt with it in in that clause.
O K，我噉我頭先可能睇唔到你呢句，噉係咪即係話，如果唔係指定嘅吸煙嘅區域，就全部唔準食煙？O K。
有咁有冇嗰個嘅指定吸煙區域嗰個嘅map話到畀我哋聽，你邊一啲區係會指定可以吸煙嘅咧？Not yet. I think we haven't know until the park is designed and built, and clearly we'd then look at know how we're going to manage that issue as part of the.
噉我哋希望喺適合時候會再翻翻嚟畀我哋睇一睇嗰度嗰個情況。
啊！不過你都留意啦，好似康文署所有嘅場地都唔準吸煙，公園係咪啊，馮太？
即係我哋佔大部分，康文署佔大部分嘅公園咧都係非吸煙嘅，係唔準吸煙嘅。但係亦都有個別嘅公園得到區議會嘅同意咧，係可以有一啲指定吸煙區嘅，但係得要同區議會商量嘅嗰啲。因為我知道維園咁大個區都冇㗎啊，係。
嚇，房屋署就有，但康文署好大部分公園都冇。
即係基本上係係唔可以食煙，除非係一個指定嘅吸煙區，而有得到。但係你個指定吸煙區係區議會定啊嘛，係嘛？咁但係好多都區議會實實唔制㗎啦，係嘛？因為定咗畀人鬧㗎喎，你影響到噉，所以好多公園甚至維維多利亞公園咁大都冇嘅嚇。噉我諗你西九如果設吸
入園區嘅時候，你你憑咩嘢設咧？有冇做consultation咧？你即係揾嚟搞啊！你自己諗清楚點做應該諮詢下噉啊。主席噉，我覺得應該要諮詢下喎。呢個問題噉啊，係咯嚇，因為因為唔單止係香港，你仲有好多遊客嚟㗎嘛，係咪咁要好清晰講邊度可以食煙，邊度唔可以食煙。我
我又覺得唔需要一刀切，切曬話度度都唔得。即係如果唔係到時最斬佢違規嘅啫，噉你不如話我合理地劃定邊啲區域，即係邊一條街、邊一個corner。咁呢啲其實其他城市都做到嘅，佢哋。噉我諗呢個再日後再，如果佢認為得嘅需要嘅時候，就做諮詢啦，好嘛？OK，我。
我哋今個議程就講完㗎啦，下一個議程咧係議程第二咧，就係依個演藝劇場同埋演藝廣場嘅發展區嘅新進展。噉啊，請誒西九管理局啊介紹誒，或者我介紹少少先啊，主席係啦。誒，今呢一個議題議程咧就係講演藝劇場同埋藝術廣場發展區發展嘅最新進展。
嘅咁誒，為咗提升西九文化區裏邊各項設施嘅設計效益啦，同埋喺營運方面能夠產生到一啲協同效應咧，西九管理局係喺檢討咗第二期嘅各個表演場地之後咧，而家係一個新嘅建議嘅。佢建議咧就係將原本喺第二期裏邊嘅當代表演中心同埋中型劇場，即係近誒二。
中型劇場二，即係近住戲曲中心嗰兩個設施嘅部分嘅誒設施咧，會放放埋喺呢一個藝術廣場發展區裏面嘅演藝劇場。我哋英文叫Lyric Theatre，嗰度係一拼係設計並且咧重組咧成為一個叫演藝綜合劇場嘅。咁重組之後嘅呢一個嘅演藝綜合劇場咧，有幾個大。
嘅變動嘅第一咧就係個座位咧係由一千二百個座位咧係加到一千四百五十個座位，並且咧為咗誒回應電影業界嘅要求咧，會安裝一啲數碼投射嘅設施嚟到畀電影放映嘅。咁頭先我提到就係話喺當代熱電表演中心咧同埋小型劇場咧裏邊咧就有兩個設。
意思係會搬咗去呢一個演藝嘅綜合劇場，一個就係一個六百個位同埋二百個位嘅劇場嘅。咁咧，但係亦都咧會繼續保留呢個駐區團藝團中心，係畀呢個舞蹈藝團咧係使用。噉我哋預計咧呢一個嘅綜演藝綜合劇場咧，誒會係喺二零二零年咧左右咧係可以落。
嘅噉，關於成個我哋叫做藝術廣場發展區啦，叫做小西九啦個大江嘅設計工作咧，亦都進行得如火如荼㗎啦。誒，頭之前大家都聽過誒誒呢個博物館M Plus啦，同埋頭先我提過嘅演藝綜合劇場咧，呢兩個主要設施之外咧，區裏邊咧仲會有其他嘅文化藝術設施嘅，包括一啲零售餐。
飲消閒嘅設施同埋辦公室住宅發展項目，咁呢個嘅誒一啲嘅公共空間咧，亦都會可以作一啲街頭表演、户外演出嘅嘅活動嘅。咁而家我咧係請管理局嘅項目推展行政總監陳文偉博士咧，係以投影嘅影片咧向各位介紹呢兩方面嘅最新嘅發展嘅。多謝主席。好啊，唔該。
係誒，長哥先嚇，請你掌握時間，因為我哋今次就冇得stand嘅。
係，多謝主席。誒，我知道我技術員而家做緊呢個誒投影片嘅更換啦，或者我誒趁佢做緊呢個更換嘅時候咧，同大家講一講我哋誒呢一個嘅誒演藝劇場啦，同埋呢個誒藝術誒演藝劇場同埋藝術廣場嘅發展嘅。
咁誒喺依個誒舊年咧，我哋已經咧就係同大家講過咧，就係話依個誒誒藝術廣場嘅發展咧，我哋想我係用一個嘅重點嘅區域嘅發展。咁依個重點區域咧，就誒包括咗誒M加啦，亦都係誒。
而家等一等，或者而家嗰個誒PowerPoint出咗嚟啦。
誒呢個區域咧，其實咧包含咗M加啦，亦都有其他喺呢個誒顯藝藝術廣場附近嘅好多嘅誒設施嘅。
好，或者我再睇一睇啦。大家睇翻呢個圖裏邊咧，噉我哋依一個咧就係嗰個藝術廣場個區域。咁點解會係一個重點發展嘅區域咧？或者我哋話希望可以有一啲誒早啲可以二零二零年完成咧？咁因為依個區域本身咧有佢嘅地理上嘅好處，因為亦都有一將來咧會有一條。
橋咧係直接去到依個九龍站，咁依個區域裏邊咧亦都包含咗M加博物館、誒演藝劇場，亦都有其他嘅零售、餐飲、消閒嘅措施誒嘅設施，亦都有辦公室、住宅，咁所有嘅設施咧其實都一個可以講係一個小型嘅西九。
咁或者我哋講一講咧，咁點解我哋會係重點睇依樣嘢咧？就亦都有喺依一個區域裏邊咧，我哋有個演藝劇場。咁至於演藝劇場咧，嗰個設計咧已經喺二零一四年五月咧就開展咗。噉我哋亦都咧係誒請咗個設計師咧，就係U N S T。
同埋呢個誒誒A.G.L.G.咧，就去做呢個設計。咁有得大家咧知道咧，喺我哋舊年誒三月嗰陣時，都同啊各位彙報過咧，依一個嘅演藝劇場咧，我哋嗰個原先嘅設計咧，會係一個千二座位嘅場。
嚟咧，同埋個定定位咧就係以舞蹈為主嘅，咁亦都可以用嚟舉辦話劇同埋音樂劇嘅表演嘅。咁當我哋喺二零一四年五月誒委聘咗我哋顧問誒設計嗰陣時咧，我哋同佢咧就進行咗好多檢討，咁咧亦都係因應咗當時。
喺個文化區嘅表演場地啦，同埋設計效益咧，同埋營運方面咧，希望可以係更加優化我哋嘅設計。咁或者大家咧就會再睇一睇咧，喺我哋誒原先嘅劇場嘅誒鋪排咧。如果你喺左邊咧，喺演藝劇場咧，我哋。
嗰度嘅左邊呢個位置咧，主要咧係一個演藝劇場啦，一個住區嘅藝團嘅中心。而喺右邊呢個近住一個高鐵嘅位置咧，我哋有兩個表演場地嘅，一個咧係當代表演中心，亦都有一個中型劇場喺度嘅。
噉我哋而家咧，亦都喺我根據我哋嘅重組同埋整合咧，我哋咧就希望咧就將佢咧就演變為咧喺左邊嘅演藝劇場咧就加咗小劇場、中型嘅劇場同埋一個駐區嘅藝團中心。咁至於右邊咧，我哋剩翻咧就會當代表演中心同埋。
住區嘅藝術中心嘅，至於而家依度依個位置誒騰出嚟咧，我哋將會係誒研究將來嘅其他嘅藝術嘅用途嘅。
咁至於話演藝劇場將來我哋嘅誒設計會係點樣咧？噉就會喺裏邊咧，原先嘅千二座位咧，我哋希望咧可以增加到一千四百五十個座位。
咁咧，亦都會係安裝呢個數碼投射設備咧，就放影誒電影嘅。
咁咧主要咧，我哋都係回應咗電影業界嘅要求啦，噉樣。咁至於喺呢個同樣呢個位置咧，我哋亦都希望咧就會加咗個小劇場、中型劇場。
呢啲噉樣嘅誒改動咧，我哋咧亦都同呢個誒各個嘅表演團體咧，有一連串嘅會議咧，就解釋呢個點解會係一個整合同埋重新安排嘅。咁咧亦都係啦，將來我哋嘅點樣去管理啊，個整個設施點樣去展設備設計啊，噉我哋同佢大家咧都喺個藝術。
團體咧，仲有嗰啲誒反應嘅。
轉銷完成時咧，我哋都有個好好理想嘅反應，關於依一個噉樣嘅改動嘅。
咁至於其實將來嗰個誒設計會點咧？睇翻依幅圖咧，噉我哋會係係可以係更有經濟效益噉樣去做一個噉樣嘅設計。咁將依一個噉樣嘅同一個地地裏邊咧，有一千四百五十個座位嘅演藝劇場啦、中型劇場啦，同埋一個小劇場嘅二百座位。
位嘅。
當然喺個設計裏邊咧，亦都牽涉到誒可能嘅交通配套啊、上落客貨啊嗰啲咧，我哋亦都會做咗一係列嘅誒所謂嘅研究，令到可以成誒可以做得到出嚟嘅。
咁至於誒成個嘅藝術誒廣場嘅設計又如何咧？噉我哋咧就獲得到一個規劃許可咧，就發展更具規模嘅設計喺依度。噉我哋咧就因為依個成個嘅設計非常重要咧，我哋希望咧就可以促進到大家藝術家嘅交流合作咧，同埋大。
大家市民都可以參與，同埋係用呢個噉樣嘅場地嘅。咁呢個全個設計咧，你就睇到咧喺中間咧就會有一個誒Art Square，真係嘅廣場喺度嘅。咁成個設計咧，我哋亦都咧就係用咗我哋嘅誒公園設計團隊咧去發展同埋設計。
咁希望咧，成個設計咧就可以咧，就更加有活力，咁令到大家將來可以用呢個噉樣嘅誒小廣場，呢個廣場咧就用咗好多嘅誒活動嘅。
咁成個整體嘅發展咧，亦都誒希望可以咧好靈活噉樣咧係活動，同埋咧就促進呢個藝術家可以交流。咁當然，例如譬如話有個好好好好誒好嘅電影嘅展覽咧，可以有一個紅地氈式嘅嘅嘅入場啊，或者藝術嘅活動咧，我哋都喺考慮之。
你。
咁呢個嘅誒廣場裏邊咧，亦都有好重要嘅誒零售、餐飲、消閒嘅設計喺度。頭先亦都講過咧，呢個廣場咧，除咗藝術嘅設施咧，亦都會有辦公室、住宅嘅發展項目。咁呢啲當然嘅可能嘅可行性嘅嘅嘅設計咧，我哋亦～
都係進行緊喺依個誒誒誒可能性嘅研究。
咁即係話，全部其實關於其實探討緊財務嘅可能性啊，亦都會喺包含裏邊咧。
咁至於其他嘅設計咧，我哋會係包括埋其他誒住宅發展項目啦、文化藝術設施嘅嘅嘅鋪排咧，亦都喺成個整體嘅計劃裏邊咧，我哋係研究緊嘅。
咁或者呢個係簡單嘅報告，多謝主席。好啊，再冇補充，係阿馮生。
誒誒，主席嘅補充。
誒，主席，我補充少少誒喺誒呢一個轉變裏邊，喺由誒藝術界，尤其是舞蹈界同埋戲劇界角度嚟到講咧，有幾個好處嘅。第一咧就係將一啲誒將將一個中型劇場同埋一個小型嘅劇場，佢設施落成嘅時間咧係由原定嘅二零二。
二年係提前到二零二零年左右，咁對誒戲劇界嚟講咧，佢哋係非常之歡迎呢一個誒噉樣嘅轉變，令到佢有一啲戲劇嘅設施可以提早得到可以做到出嚟。咁另外演藝劇場佢本身嗰個誒設施嗰個座位數目由一二誒零零間增加到一四五零，咁對。
誒好多嘅演藝界朋友嚟，好講咧，佢哋要即係一個比較大型嘅演出，嚟喺個誒想吸引到多啲觀眾咧。呢個對佢嚟講都係一個好嘅安排。咁另外，其實呢一個轉變咧，就會令到喺誒誒演藝誒廣場呢一邊嘅設施，再加埋M plus，再加埋公園其他嘅設施咧，就會喺。
二零二零年之前，好歸一咁發展成為一個綜合嘅一個藝術嘅設施，有室內同埋室外嘅一個部分。噉我哋喺個同藝術界嘅溝通裏邊咧，喺呢方面裏邊亦都得到藝術界嘅好好直接嘅一個支持。多謝主席。好嘅，如如果冇補充，我哋就誒畀。
誒，下我哋嘅議員發問啦。O.K.，陳志全。
長主席嚇時間四分鐘啊。O K，誒，我想問翻藝術演藝劇場嘅藝術定位嘅問題。咁文件裏邊都係話佢係以舞蹈為主啦，但係亦都可以用作舉辦其他唔同類型嘅表演藝術啊。咁其實呢一個誒。
演藝劇場嗰個舞蹈為主嘅意思係你哋會舞蹈表演嘅申請優先啦，定係你哋根本同誒合作團體有個配額，即係每年係會有幾多場嘅舞蹈表演噉樣咧？點解我提出呢個問題咧？因為當我哋討論咗咁多藝術定位嘅時候咧，我真係～
真係好怕，最後好似紅磡香港體育館咁個名就叫做體育館，但係最後就係以演唱會為主。雖然呢個可能政府覺得成功㗎啊個使用率啊嗰個賺錢嘅角度嚟睇，咁今次呢一個演藝劇場個名就比較中性啦，佢唔係改咗做舞蹈館啊噉樣。但我見到誒，譬如。
都話加咗回應電影界嘅要求，加咗誒呢個數碼投射設施，即係話都好靈活嘅。他朝亦可以變戲院咁都得嘅。咁噉，如果係噉樣嘅話，咁舞蹈為主係你哋嘅起初嘅意願，到到最後會唔會又變咗靈活運用啊？即係邊個賺錢，邊個？
多人嚟就會用咗嗰樣嘢咧，噉樣。
Okay, perhaps to understand the overall context of what we've tried to do. No, it's a much more cost-efficient building. It's much more. It provides many more options for local companies. That under the old proposal of the 1,200 seats.
It would have had very limited capacity to be able to be utilised by those companies that could use a 1,200 seat theatre. What we now have is, first off, the issue for the ballet companies, the larger dance companies. They can go up to 1,450 seats, or they can use the 600 seat theatre, or they can use the 250
50 seat theatre, there has been a request articulated in this committee before about the film community wanting to have limited access to a 1450 seat theatre for film projects, openings like the Hong Kong Film Festival and and other major.
film projects， so we see that as part of the use of it. But what it does actually give the companies is many more options as to how they can use it. It gives us as the management of the the complex the ability to look at those companies that need capacity up to one thousand, four hundred and fifty.
用大劇院，但對於那些觀眾數量較少的，則用600座的。所以我們認為這是個更大的機會，是在時間框架內，部分是因為XRL的延誤，所以到2020年。
to give the Hong Kong companies a number of options within a building that at the moment would not be finished until some time beyond that. If we went with the existing proposal of just one theatre on that site to be shared by the the dance companies and a number of other
Organisations. O.K. 主席啊，唔係啊，餘生有啲補充畀啊，餘生補充啊。
我本。
誒以舞蹈以舞蹈為主咧，其實有兩個意思嘅。誒第一個意思咧，就係呢個場地將來咧，我哋誒舞蹈嘅使用咧就會有優先，呢個第一個意思。第二個意思咧，就係當誒設計師喺設計呢個場地裏邊咧，裏邊有啲誒設計嘅特色咧，係會最方便舞蹈嘅使用。
主要係依兩個設施，因為誒舞蹈誒藝術界一路都希望咧西九嘅場地咧會有特色同埋會有誒性格化，咁所以咧我哋喺唔同嘅場地裏邊咧都會有一個誒主要嘅一個藝術嘅形式，譬如話戲曲中心就係一個戲曲嘅場地，其他誒話劇嘅場劇場就一啲誒戲劇嘅。
個主要嘅場地噉樣，主席一句啫，舞蹈優先嘅意思，可唔可以解釋多幾句咧？係咪即係舞蹈可以攞場地先？誒舞蹈優先誒優先嘅意思咧，就即係話喺將來嗰個誒租場嘅政策裏邊啦，同埋喺我哋誒誒投放資源去舉辦節目裏邊嘅時候，喺呢個場地裏邊咧，舞蹈都有個優先。
O K.
下一位，誒，陳婉霞。主席啊，我哋真係立法會好淒涼。
唔合理啊！今日我係五個會，我而家撞我個會未入去開嘅，即係都係撞到七彩，撞到七彩。誒，我我想講真係好遺憾，我哋而家啲時間冇時間開會，所以我同啲同陳志全投訴，我唔掂啊！我又同啊其他啲泛民朋友講話唔掂啊！而家係好慘，我哋咁撞法。邊個開呢個會嗱？呢個會好重要嘅會，佢今。
交兩份好大文件，一個附件，一個附例，一個就有關而家佢設計具體。噉我頭先喺上拍咧，就已經一口氣講曬咁多。噉你始終唔能夠展開啲討論嗱。我我先講咧，第一個附例咧，我講喺上上拍。誒，上邊唔講㗎啦嚇。唔係主席，你邊講兩句？你講咗我都唔畀佢答。你唔緊要，我講嗱，我我上。
我強調一樣嘢，你話下一季度開始，我哋明年嘅七月份就結出嚟會啦。你估我哋好順攤咩？我覺得應該要提早啲上嚟，你因翻時間同翻政府講，佢唔答我冇所謂。另外一個咧，我就講翻而家呢個問題咧，呢個問題就情況點咧？我就覺得而家咧，聽阿陳生講即係阿博士講咧，你加加加加多。
嘢，我就想問你，特別你對啲喺而家原來嗰個誒演藝劇場個附近，你要加搭一啲嘢，就有關啲黑匣嗰啲嘢嘅。咁聽佢哋嘅文化界講咧，係好擔心你加呢啲嘢嘅建築成本更加大。所以我上一派就講，點解可能會擺喺而家？我哋喺未來個公
遠嘅黑盒裏邊加上咧，嗱呢個希望你，你到時唔好又要加成本加錢，我哋真係面對住西九加錢加到我哋雲陀陀，呢個我覺得阿陳生，我係要你畀個答案嘅。第一個問，第二個問題咧，我就想睇個問題，就而家你剛才講嗰啲有關，即係呢啲噉嘅表演嘅場地咧，你答阿陳志全嗰。
問題，我希望你用八字、一字寫到明，就嗱，我哋以美誒舞蹈為主嘅，我擔心當佢經濟效益同一啲正常嘅文化團體入嚟嘅時候咧，你要用咗啲經濟作為前提，噉我覺得呢啲你都亦都清楚啲話畀我聽，係咪可以八字一字做咧？唔該，主席。好啊，誒，朱浩達個場地問題啦。誒，主席或者我打。
阿鄧亞勤議員關於依個誒成本啦，我哋點解其中一個原因咧，就將依個誒演藝劇場同埋啲小劇場、中型劇場一齊噉樣合埋一一齊咧？其中有一個原因咧，就係可以增加個成本效益嘅，因為如果你誒每一個建築物單棟噉樣起咧，我哋亦都睇過咧，如果。
你將某一啲嘅所謂我哋叫back-up house，即係誒後長盤後邊嘅設施可以有個共用咧，其實係有成本效益可以做得出嚟。噉我覺得呢個其實一個最主要原因咧，我哋誒係喺一個誒成本控制方面咧，我哋都睇到呢樣嘢嘅。陳生，我嘗試問你，你能否將如果你唔加上原來價錢？
同佢加上之後要加多幾錢咧？你話畀我聽喎。如果唔係你好似今日過咗之後咧，又再奉旨我哋去加嘢，跟住再唔知加幾多錢喎？我哋好怕，好似Amperex噉樣。
Okay, Mr. Lee.
We we have a discussion in May about the overall cost. Clearly, by that stage, we will have designed the building. There is no question. The idea of putting the three buildings together makes it much more cost effective than building the three buildings as was originally proposed. So we will be able to come back.
once we've progressed with the design, with a closer idea of what we're talking about in terms of the overall cost of the building, it fits within the budgets that we're working with. and阿阿阿阿連生，我明嘅。我而家問阿陳博士，你將而家未改變嘅價錢同你將來搭埋上，好似
the the cost of the existing building was one of the issues for us in that the indicative cost was about 2.4 billion dollars, you know less than the cost of the ZHU, but it only covered the cost of one building, and and so that's part of the reasoning behind why we've gone.
要試下，
有成本。好，黃碧雲。
主席，誒，我哋而家即係成個西九文化區咧，最大鑊咧就係即係慢慢即係由大西九變做縮水，做小西九。
咁而家咧嗰個原來嗰個嘅誒設計嗰度咧，即係你而家喺誒東邊嗰邊嘅當代表演中心同埋駐園區藝術中心嗰度咧，你而家又又得咗一半出嚟。
嗰半唔知起乜嘢，同埋起唔起都唔知。
噉係咪又交翻去做地產項目定係做文化項目咧？當時係第日係會做咩咧？即係你嗰度縮咗一橛喎。嗱，如果你計翻條數咧～
計翻條數咧，你而家喺嗰個誒演藝劇場嗰度話加多二百五十個位，去到一四五零。
咁但係你喺東面嗰邊原來有三個黑匣劇場。
咁咧就總共加埋嗰邊咧係有四個劇場嘅。而家咧你縮水，你嗰度咧係講嗰四個劇場原本係預計咧加埋係有一千四百個座位嘅。咁如果你得走一半，跟住搬一啲位過去，誒演藝劇場一來一回，其實你而家係少咗六百個位。
跟住仲好逼添。
嗱，因為你原先嗰度係六六百四百二五零一五零，有有四個喺度㗎嘛。
咁如果你而家噉樣得走咗，剩翻兩個劇場喺東邊，噉係得一個四百，一個一百五十，即係得翻五百五十嘅啫。喎，噉你原先嗰度已經係少咗啦。噉你搬就加，即係嗰邊就減，嗰邊係加少少。即係我唔知你係唔係可以可以喺度解釋清楚。同埋咧，而家我覺得咧最大鑊嘅。
問題就係咧。
如果畀你哋揀啊，你係用翻原先方案，你覺得係好啲啊，定係而家呢個方案咧？而家你係咪喺無奈底下，因為高鐵個項目阻住你嗰塊地，交唔到過嚟，你預期咧唔知遙遙期等幾遠，不如搬一啲過去嗰邊起住先。即係你究竟係咪因為因為高鐵嘅項目？
揾唔到塊地，同埋係咪任佢拖咧？有冇時間表幾時交翻嚟？係咪任佢拖？佢一日拖你十年八載，噉你就嗰度都唔使起㗎咯。即係我想問下西九管理局係咪完全被動地無奈地係因為即係高鐵嗰度唔交翻塊地翻嚟？你又無冇即係無奈嘅係咪噉樣？
點樣咧？
誒。
The budget for the site and the whole plan for the site is clearly one of the issues that we've been talking about for a long period of time. It was made very clear over the course of the last year that we were looking at batch one, batch two, which were covered by the existing budget, subject to obviously Legco's agreement.
on the funding of the basement and the associated infrastructure, what we have proposed in in this proposal is that we try and deliver as many of the venues as we can by 2020. We would have two venues in the ZHU, 1100 and 200 seats. What we're
是到帶上線，by two thousand and twenty，three venues in the lyric of fourteen five thousand six hundred two hundred and fifty。 We would have the venue of free space in the park between four hundred and fifty nine hundred seats。 The ten thousand seat outdoor venue in the park， the M plus museum and the
藝術 pavilion， which would all be completed and operational by 2020。 The issue of what happens with the remaining venues in Batch Two and Batch Three is clearly something that will be an ongoing issue of discussion with the government, with the Ledgeco subcommittee as we go forward.
但現在，我們嘗試要做嘅係，畀盡量嘅場地畀藝術界同香港市民，盡量喺可達嘅預算同規劃限制內。明顯，XRL嘅延誤對場地嘅交付有啲影響，但更重要。
on the the issue of the integrated basement, and until the basement is done, you can't build things above the basement. Okay.有冇少到嗰啲嗰啲座位？可唔可以解釋下？啊，定係答呢個問題？冇少到。
我啲冇打特。
上嗰個數字其實多咗嘅，就冇少到。OK，好，下一位劉慧卿。
啊，主席啊！
唉，其實呢個呢個呢個西九咧，同埋呢個高鐵咧，就真係真係搞到香港雞毛鴨血啊！即係頭先黃碧雲議員問嗰啲，噉佢點搞啊？而家高鐵都唔知點樣點樣收貨，又冇一地兩檢，我都話最好揾啲泥填翻住嗰度啦。你嘅挖開曬。
咁而家就影響埋西九，就真係咧，真係真係好好大劑咯。真係我我都唔知真係點收科啊！第日日訂又超支啊，出嚟啲嘢又唔啱數啊，噉樣咧，唉，真係有有排搞啊！主席嗱，噉我問問下啦，演藝界嗰度咧，頭先講就話演藝界歡迎啊。
但係演藝界有啲同我哋一路講咧，就係好好嬲嘅，覺得你哋冇諮詢佢啊。佢哋甚至有啲咧就希望有自己個場地，又可以做即係練啦嚇，然後又表演。咁而家又多咗啲嘢啦。咁喺呢方面同佢哋有冇傾得清楚咧？係咪佢哋都好接受咧？同埋嗰個咩公園咧，主席？
哇！我睇落去頭都暈曬。嗰個藝術廣場啊，你有冇睇到啊？好多個八字喺度噉樣嘅咯，即係你呢個就好正。上邊望落去啦，但係係咪真係真係大家覺得好好咩？即係好頭暈嘅喎。呢個望落去同埋最後咧，就問下嗰啲誒賣飛嗰個安排啊。
即係希望第日快啲起好啦。你話二零二零啊嗰啲，即係人哋講就係而家康文署嗰個賣飛咧就好好唔得掂嘅。啊啊，秘書啊，秘書長你都知啦。咁嗰陣時都講過話要即係改革佢，不如改革康文署咧，真係真係都好勇敢。咁呢度而家開始咗去做啲嘢未咧？
Okay, Mr. Liech. First part of the question, Mr. Chairman. We have done extensive consultation with all of the arts companies in the dance, theatre and associated sectors. We as of yet had no dissent from the proposal that we're putting on the table for.
the extension of the lyric from the one theatre model to the three theatre model. Those conversations are continuing. We have offered the theatre, dance and related performing communities the opportunity to be involved in the design of the building as it progresses over the coming months.
O.K.其他嗰啲咧？其他啲。嗰個藝術廣場咧，嗰個係邊個？藝術廣場係咪就係個圖噉嘅款喺度好似眼都花噉嘅？誒，嗰個廣場而家係初步設計啫，我哋跟住都會優化嘅。依個真係話翻你聽個位置啊，地方啫。誒，There's a lot of things about this project that make us feel dizzy.
But I guess probably one of them is the issue around how we're going to get the decisions through the ledgeo for the funding of the important infrastructure and integrated basement works. The outer square seems to us the best way of being able to provide as much of this project.
在最短的可能時間，放棄掉基座和XRL項目的麻煩，從我們的角度看，這就是我們推動三劇場模式的原因。至於Artis Square，以及商業活動，兩大場館。
Zam Plus and the Lyric Theatre complex. I guess because Mr Lynch is leaving us, that's why I guess you are more forthcoming with your views. Many things make us dizzy. It's more than dizzy. I think we're furious. What about the ticketing arrangements? Well, no, we don't have any theatres yet. I think ticketing.
comes after you built the the venues, so we're looking at. I guess it takes quite a long time to sort out L C S D, isn't it? It's not our responsibility to sort out L C S D. So you will have a different ticketing arrangement from other L C S D venues. We haven't resolved that issue yet.嗱，主席你睇啊，乜鬼都係。
又有個處喺度，佢做嗰啲嘢咧就唔可以搬過嚟，因為大家覺得唔好嚇。無論管公園又好，而家管呢啲場地，即係因為佢嗰套嘢咧又又唔改革到喎。其實改革到就全香港好利民㗎嘛。咁即係總言之，就唔係淨係眯埋眼睇住西九啦。你仲有好多其他嘅設。
設施，我哋都希望有啲好嘅管理啦，主席。好好好好，啊，副主席啊，多謝主席。
主席，我即係三番四次講過咧，即係我。
好希望咧，誒唔會話因為當年啦，特區政府嗰種豪情壯語、計錯數、拍曬心口，就即係令到而家咧畫虎不成反類犬啦。因為呢一個項目咧，的確係對於香港嚇係。
喺世界嘅文化藝術版圖上面咧，能夠成為另一個亮點咧，係非常之重要嘅。而家對於香港嘅人民嘅質素啊，係有好重要嘅關鍵影響嘅。所以我成日都強調咧，呢個係一個只可以成功，不可以失敗嘅一個。
項目啦。
咁即係近年嘅發展，當然我見到咧，似乎就係誒政府都想誒盡量開放多啲可以開放得嘅場地，令到香港人咧就即係覺得係自己係持份者啊，啊，即係覺得自己係擁有呢個，即係個。
咁值得珍惜嘅一個文化藝術嘅項目，噉就可以咧遲啲咧嚟再攞錢加碼咧，就忘記咗當年政府嘅錯誤啦。噉就希望可以水到渠成。咁呢個咧我都係覺得一個高明嘅做法。嗱，我而家見到咧今日嘅。
介紹裏邊咧就包括咧一個演藝劇場咧就變成演藝綜合劇場。噉我都明白個苦心嘅。咁呢個苦心咧就係即係你唔知道而家嗰個噉嘅高鐵搞成點啊嘛，即係拖下一年就拖下一年，咁都唔知佢想搞到幾時，幾時畀翻你去。
起又唔知幾時咧？嗰個地庫可以追通入，亦都係好難預測。咁所以咧，我諗個苦心咧就係即係將嗰啲中型劇場、小劇場咧，即係嗰陣時叫黑盒劇場嗰度咧，就有部分搬咗過嚟先噉樣啦。我都明白嗰個邏輯嘅。咁但係我想問清楚咧，就係噉啊嗱，如果
我哋即係第日真係噉樣做啦，照而家呢個誒現方案咁嚟到行事咧，咁嗰個地庫咧，政府整咗就嚟嚟攞錢起啊！
咁如果第日真係有咩冬瓜豆腐，其他部分嗰啲地庫追通唔到，咁而家呢個地庫起咗出嚟係有冇有冇作用嘅咧？即係係咪自己有個地牢喺度咁？即係自己喺嗰度，但係博唔到去，譬如戲曲誒誒中心噉樣，會唔會出現噉樣情況嘅？有冇預見㗎？
好，邊位答？
gentlemen, the answer to the question is that there are basements under M Plus and under the Lyric, which is the first phase of the integrated basement that then connect to the rest of the integrated basement that is relevant to Batch Two and Batch Three. Clearly, the
Issue that we're dealing with in the next applications, I think coming to the Ledgeco, relate very much to the end of the site around Arthur Square. But clearly, we'll be able to operate quite independently of the decisions and the time frame on what happens with the rest of the basement.
And the other buildings that are affected by the XRL project.
阿陳博士有唔有補充啊？
即係如果係誒最壞嘅打算誒走唔通嘅話咧，喺佢嗰個去到New Victoria，即係話嗰個應該係劇場嘅誒地底嘅通道咧，都可以係有standalone嘅嚇。
O.K.，我仲想跟一跟就係嗰個黑盒劇場咧。你原來嗰個黑盒劇場係咪而家嗰個唔起㗎啦？亦或係誒，即係縮小佢嘅規模，抑或點㗎？
阿阿如生。
嗯。
原來嗰個黑海劇場喺當代表演中心嘅黑海劇場咧，係移咗過嚟誒演嚟綜合劇場裏邊嗰個小劇場，其實誒個座位數目係一樣嘅。
即係唔起㗎啦，嗰個原來嗰個係嘛？誒，原來咧就誒喺原來嘅誒誒，即係當代表演中心裏邊咧，仍然留低一個誒四百位一個劇場，同埋一百五十位一個劇場，仲有嘅，即係整體嘅劇場嘅數字其實係冇改變，整體個數誒座位數值係亦都係增加。
吉咗嚇，咁咁吉咗出嚟嗰部分咧，即係原來即係而家嗰個原原來方案咧，就比起將來方案係大啲㗎嘛，咁吉咗出嚟嗰部分係愛嚟做咩啊？
係。
會 happen with that space? Clearly, it would be available as one of the options into the future of how it would be used if we're able to accelerate and move forward the lyric theatre complex.
O.K.仲有冇提問？誒第二輪啦，我我想問一問先。噉我想問清楚咧，即係話而家你噉樣搬落嚟啊，係咪將第三期有一啲項目搬咗落嚟？你搬落嚟嘅原因係咪真係驚住？
將來唔做第三期，所以先做依個縮水劑狗先係嘛。即係如果唔係咧，你變咗成個西狗有部分演藝啊，或者其他嘅設施。They're actually batch two facilities being incorporated into to batch one. We haven't touched at all any of the batch three facilities.
which are the big venues and the the spaces affected by the railway. I guess the issue is not for us to determine what's going to happen with batch three. I think it's clearly will be subject to future funding, future timing and.
未來進展， on batch one and batch two.
咪嗱，你而家噉樣誒，即係擠埋一堆啦，同埋有啲劇場已經又將啊用用用多咗用途啦。電影你都放埋，噉你頭先同阿餘生你講嗰啲，即係場地性格啊，嗰啲咁咧，完全都係背道而馳嘅，即係擺埋一齊就冇性格㗎啦，係嘛？同埋互相都有影響嘅。
你個場地如果能夠係專門係做任何任和某一類型嘅表演咧，噉你景即係你即係使用啊、方便啊，同埋表演咧都會有好嘅效果嘅。而家你擺埋一齊嘅時候咧，第一你出現咗一個效果，你永遠都唔可以滿足所有嘅表演。
學認識嘅。第二咧，你又爭嘅啫，互相嗰度爭嘅啫，係嘛？你你話畀佢舞蹈優先，咁即係其他啲唔使優先，噉你點都要搞掂。啊，冇一個專門係做劇場啊，即係做誒話劇啊，或者專門係放電影嘅嘅。
設施是得。如果唔係，你噉樣擺埋一碟咧，你即係你始終咧，你出現啲問題咧，影響好大係嘛？咁入境，大家一齊鬥入境，大家一齊拆啊！大家一齊搬嚟搬去咧，你自己互相影響。同埋我都想知道下，喂，一齊散場點算咧？呢度話你加埋去。
話一加加加加埋二千幾，咁雖然話可以錯開啲時間，但係而家文化中心錯開時間，佢都係得兩個劇院錯開時間都好多好逼人啦。如果你三四個劇院錯開時間嘅時候，你會出現點樣走咧？係嘛？點樣去疏導啲客乘客咧？你諗都冇諗嘅喎，係咪可以幾？
Well, that's that's not true, Mr. Chairman. We've thought about it a lot. You know, there are thousands of theatre complexes in China, England, America where you share theatres. It's a much more efficient use of space of resources. And clearly, the programming policy has not yet been.
But the idea of being able to share theatre space and dance space is a very well established concept, both in Hong Kong and in most other parts of the world. We see it as a much more effective way of being able to both get audiences in and out to provide quality experiences.
And to ensure that they're utilised to the maximum of their capacity, the demand for dance space in that space would not sustain the idea of three theatres. So clearly, the mix of theatre, film and dance will lead to a much more cost-effective way.
of operating the venue and a much more attractive option, I think, for audiences and for the people using the Westcalleen site.
啊！我我就好似副主席講啦，就立主前照啦，我就未從來未見過世界上有一個萬能嘅劇場咧，做乜都係得嘅嚇噉啊！睇下，但係你頭先都冇嘗覆我咧，即係你點樣去控制啲人流啊，疏散啲人羣？That's I would beg to differ, Mr. Chairman. I think most complex
任何在世界，無論是悉尼歌劇院、林肯中心在紐約，或是國家表演藝術中心在北京，應該只能放電影㗎嘛嘛噉，即係唔好坑我。雖然我未去過嚇，咁但係我覺得。Many of them do show movies at various stages. The movie thing is really only.
An addition of technology to be able to utilise them for the for the number of events that are happening.
唉，噉啊！
睇住點啦，好嘛？第二輪，黃碧雲。
啊，主席，誒，即係我覺得誒，西九管理局咧。
個主席啊，而家應該係司長啊，仲係。
應該司長咧要交翻，即係要同港鐵講咧，交翻個時間表出嚟，幾時交地？因為其實一早係有時間表，幾時交翻笪地過嚟畀西九文化區，唔會阻住呢邊嘅。噉我覺得而家係咁飲佢哋噉樣，中意拖幾耐，我覺得係有問題嘅。即係司長應該出嚟交翻個時間表，就唔好。
阻住曬成個西九呢邊嘅建設嗱，而家噉樣做法咧，即係權宜之計嚟嘅啫。即係我睇到係誒，但係咧就。
今日講嘅咧，就主要都係講誒第一批、第二批嗰一啲嘅誒建設。
咁但係裏邊咧都係講緊舞蹈啊、話劇啊、誒電影啊嗰啲。咁但係音樂咧就冇曬咯。咁音樂係咪就要等到第三期嗰度嗰啲嘅music centre啊嗰啲誒出嚟先至有咧？即係如果唔係嘅話，第一、第二期我哋想去西金。
文化區聽音樂就冇嘅咯喎，可唔可以咁講啊？
I think we've made clear before, as has the the chairman of the West Kalloon board, that the music centre is in batch three, and at this stage, that is some time after two thousand and twenty. It clearly requires the completion of the XRL, the completion of
The integrated basement and then the design and building of the the concert hall. I think the intention has always been that a concert hall should be part of West Kaloon. My farewell hope for this project is that by the time I'm still alive, there will be a concert hall.
West Kalen。啊，主席啊，嗱，我覺得噉樣咧就真係好有問題嘅，即係我哋連話去成個西九文化區想聽音樂，原來哦冇嘅handicap，即係我覺得呢個咧就唔可以接受，即係會唔會而家諗一諗，就係話你既然而家原來嗰個當代表演中心咧嗰個嗰笪地係吉咗出嚟嘅？
係咪？因為有兩個黑匣劇場搬咗過去，誒嗰個演藝劇場啊嘛。咁空出嚟嗰拮咗嗰笪地，可唔可以喺第二期嘅時候咧，就將音樂中心喺嗰度，即係誒誒起咧，而唔係等到二零二零之後都唔知幾時先至有眉目。Unfortunately, the demands
The concert hall are the most demanding of any of the venues on the site. You can't build it over the railway line, which is one of the major issues. So that the concert hall is the venue that sits there, where the arrow is pointing to. It clearly needs to avoid all of the trains.
It needs to have the most acoustic isolation. We could move it possibly down a little bit further into one of the other two major venues, but we can't move it directly into the the site that we've vacated from the the medium theatre or the centre for contemporary.
performance.
因為那係，below那個site係五個level以下ground係train line嘅終點。
咁仲有冇第二輪？如果冇咧，我都想問翻頭先你嗰個問題咧，可唔可以解答你點樣疏散啲人羣咧？如果你幾個即係嗰個誒，即係表演場地嚇。
2,400 seats no is easy. No, the concert, you know, even in the existing concert cultural centre, there's more than. No, there are many times four or five thousand seats. Sydney Opera House, five thousand five hundred seats on any night. Dispersing, there will be no issues, and we've done the traffic and.
And people studies, know that to be able to disperse the number of people losing the lyric theatre will be a very easy issue to deal with.
點會依時㗎？你點樣二千幾人？你點樣去個火車站？去個車站？點樣去個巴士站？你一齊都埋落嚟嗰條街，你有幾闊啊？嗰條街？The same way that people leave the cultural centre um on any night of the week. Cultural centre佢兩節兩個劇院，佢係唔同時間放。你嚇佢已經逼到咧。
天星小輪都爆啦嚇！嗱，你而家三個一齊去嘅時候，你點的咧？你你你你你走咗啊，冇人理喎！你翻唔翻嚟睇啊？有一件事喎，但係將來嗰啲人睇又好大鑊喎嚇！
係啊，阿馮太。
係誒，我諗呢方面咧，我哋都會同花西九嗰邊研究。而家文化中心咧就誒，我哋嘅誒大劇院咧係一千四百幾位啦，即係同誒嗰個嘅誒誒auditorium一樣啦。而音樂廳咧係大概一千三百位，咁所以人數咧應該加埋咧就比而家誒呢個演藝劇場中心咧係多。咁但係我都明白嘅，即係因為佢。
如果三個劇院一齊咧，嗰個staggering即係可能喺嗰個開場、散場嗰度咧，時間係會大家要走嘅。咁呢個我諗即係阿阿阿阿連生佢好有經驗啦。我哋康文處亦都可以就住本地嗰啲設施點樣疏散咧，可以同佢哋分享翻嗰個經驗嘅。
OK。
仲有冇其他提問？如果冇咧，我哋就誒完結呢個誒。
討論啦，係嘛？
係。
嚟再彙報下一次啊？誒幾時再翻嚟彙報啊，洪太？誒，我哋下一次嘅會議應該係五月嘅嚇。噉我哋暫時有兩個議程，係講咩啊？五月？五月唔傾，依依依大嘅五月咧，我哋就會傾好多嘢㗎。三項嘢就係西九文化計劃嘅財務狀況啊，大家都有興趣㗎啦。
嘅財務安排最新資料。第二點咧就係西九文化綜合區嘅地庫同埋個基建工程，又係大嘢啦。第三個咧就大家都好有興趣嘅啦，M Plus嘅發展最新情況。噉啊，三個咧就係喺十喺五月十九號下晝四點鐘。
我咪起碼都開兩個幾鐘頭、三個鐘頭會㗎啦。
嚇，咁咪會開到七點，開三個鐘頭會嚇，現場度。咁所以我諗冇時間。五月十九啊？係啊，咁諗呢個咧係咪再揾個時間咧？如果你哋落實咗啊，或者有啲嘢求誒，剛才議員咧提出嘅意見咧，如果你都有啲回覆咧，誒一係就書面啦，一係如果
真係需要我哋再有啲討論咧，我諗再安排時間啦，好嗎？OK。
噉我亦都想就結束之前咧，就講翻畀大家聽咧。今年五月咧，我哋有個討論咧，有關搬遷尖沙咀消防局行動支援設施嘅以及西九文化區嘅撥款建議嘅。由於政府咧就表示咧需要更多嘅時間同埋有關技術嘅事宜咧，因此咧就唔。
能夠喺五月份咧向我哋委員會咧簡介呢個項目，咁誒政府當局咧就將於稍後適當嘅時間咧確認呢個項目嘅討論時間嘅，咁即係話下次淨係傾頭先我講嗰三樣嘢啦，好冇？
咁如果冇咩問題，我多謝大家嚇，亦。
多謝阿Litch啊嘅服務，多謝。